《博物馆奇妙夜2》
(永久保存 联邦档案室)
What if this was your house? Power's out. Lights are dead.
假设这是你的家 突然断电 一片漆黑
Your little ones in their bunk bed down the hall, crying out...
小家伙们被困在双层床上 在走廊另一端房间哭喊着...
Mommy! Daddy! Come quick! I'm scared!
妈妈!爸爸!快来!我害怕!
- You need to get there, and fast. - Coming, honey! Daddy's coming!
- 你必须第一时间赶过去 - 来了宝贝!爸爸来了!
You'll need a weapon. But first, you'll need a flashlight.
你需要一件防身的家伙 但首先 你需要的是一个手电筒
But you're in the dark! What are you gonna do?
但你四周一片漆黑 你该怎么办?
How are you gonna find it? I'll tell you how.
要怎么找到手电筒? 让我来告诉你答案
The Glow-in-the-Dark Flashlight!
夜光手电筒!
That's right, folks! I'm Larry Daley of Daley Devices,
没错 朋友们! 我是戴利设备的拉瑞·戴利
and we're gonna spend the next paid-programing block
接下去的电视导购单元
rocking your world.
将令您终身难忘
And I brought along a friend to do it. George Foreman, ladies and gentlemen!
和我一起来的还有我的朋友 女士们先生们 欢迎乔治·福尔曼
Fantastic, Larry, fantastic! Isn't he fantastic, America?
棒极了 拉瑞 棒极了! 大家说他是不是很棒
But, seriously, isn't it true that just two years ago,
不过说真的 这一切都是真的吗 仅仅两年以前
you were working as a night guard at some dusty museum?
你还只是一名博物馆夜班守卫
That is true, two-time world heavyweight champ George Foreman.
没错 你是连续两届世界重量级拳王 乔治·福尔曼
I was just a regular Joe with a flashlight and a dream.
而我只是一个小人物乔 拿着夜光手电筒怀揣着一个梦
You mean a regular Larry.
应该是小人物拉瑞
But what's no joke is you're CEO of Daley Devices,
但如今你是戴利设备的首席执行官 这可是当真的
creator of such indispensable items as the Super Big Dog Bone!
你的发明已经成了我们生活的必备品 比如超级大狗骨头!
- You like that one? - The Unlosable Key Ring!
- 你们喜欢吗? - 还有防丢失钥匙圈!
Oh, yeah, that little chestnut!
哦 对 那个小栗子
And now your latest breakthrough... Say it with me, America!
而现在你又推出了最新发明 大家一起说!
The Glow-in-the-Dark Flashlight!
夜光手电筒!
Whatever the household crisis, this is Daley Devices. Can I help you?
家庭安防有保障 这里是戴利设备 有什么可以帮助您?
Tina, give this back to Stewart. I don't trust his math, okay?
蒂娜 把这份文件还给斯图尔特 他的计算能力糟透了
- That guy called again. - Again?
- 那家伙又打来了 - 又打来?
Lar! Huge news! We got the Wal-Mart meeting.
拉瑞!爆炸新闻! 沃尔玛终于同意和我们进行合作洽谈了
- No! When? - Yeah. Three days.
- 不会吧!什么时候? - 三天后
Okay, all right. We got a lot of work to do.
好吧 好的 那我们有的好准备了
Well, okay, did you just hear me say "Wal" and "Mart" together?
你有听我说吗?那可是沃尔玛
Yeah! I know, it's huge.
是!我知道 这是件大事!
So just take a second to be happy about it.
那该庆贺一下啊
All right.
好吧
You're totally making fun of me.
你真是太扫兴了
No, let's hold off on the victory parade till we close, okay?
今天全公司集体庆祝直到关门 怎么样?
You got it.
遵命
- And when does he want to meet? - They want Friday morning, 10:00 a.m.
- 他想约什么时候见面? - 礼拜五早上十点
Okay, then, you know what? Cancel that pitch
好吧 你知道该怎么做 取消推广会
for the electric saw thing with the propeller, all right?
关于螺旋推进电锯的那个 好吗?
- I just want to focus on this. - Okay.
- 我得集中思想 - 好的
- Just this. - My daughter's birthday, canceled!
- 就这样 - 我女儿的生日也泡汤了!
You can go home. I'm gonna be pretty late, okay.
你可以先回去 我会呆到很晚 好吗?
Okay, boss.
是 老板
(自然历史博物馆)
(关闭整修)
Hello! Excuse me! Unauthorized personnel!
嗨抱歉 未经许可不得入内!
If it isn't our very own Mr. Success Story.
这不是我们的一夜成名先生吗
Come for one of your nostalgia tours? I haven't seen you for a few months.
来重游故地吗? 好几个月没看到你了
Yeah, I've been busy. What's going on here?
对 我一直很忙 这里怎么回事?
Progress, so they tell me.
发展 他们这样告诉我的
The future. Behold, Natural History, version 2.0.
这是发展趋势 自然历史博物馆 2.0版
Welcome to The Museum of Natural History, where history comes to life!
欢迎来到自然历史博物馆 这里能看到最鲜活的历史
Step up, ask your question.
站出来 问出你的问题
Then let the next little boy or girl have their turn.
孩子们排好队一个一个来
Okay, where were you born?
好吧 你的出生地?
Right here in New York City, on Twentieth Street.
就在这里 纽约市 二十大街
October 27th, the year of our Lord 1858.
我生于1858年10月27日
Blah, blah, blah. History, history. Learning, learning.
历史 历史 学习 学习
Changing America, one child at a time.
改变美国人民 一次一个孩子提问
That's great. So you're adding some new interactive exhibits?
很棒 这么说你们打算增加一些这样的互动展品?
No, Mr. Daley, not adding. Replacing the old exhibits.
不 戴利先生 不是增加 而是替换所有旧的展品
- Where are they going? - Away.
- 那旧展品放去哪里? - 清理出去
We're getting rid of all this junk. The dioramas, the waxworks,
这些垃圾都要被清走 模型 蜡像
even some of the shabbier animals, like this scrawny little monkey.
还有这些破烂的动物模型 比如这只手骨嶙峋的猴子
You should be careful. He's a capuchin.
你手脚轻点 它是只僧帽猴
It's a monkey.
它是个猴子
He's a rare breed. He's a capuchin. He's not just a monkey.
它是稀有品种 它叫僧帽猴 不是只普通猴子
"Monkey", then. I said "monkey". Why be specific?
猴子 它就叫猴子 干嘛分的这么细?
When you're throwing away a monkey, you don't need the Latin name.
当你准备扔掉一只猴子时 你不需要为它取个拉丁名吧
Are you throwing him away or are you moving him?
你到底是扔掉它还是搬到别的地方?
What are you, the Primate Garbage Police? Let it go, baby.
你专管灵长垃圾吗? 算了吧 宝贝
- Whose idea was this? - Me, of course.
- 这是谁的主意? - 当然是我的
I'm in charge. Me and the board.
这事我说了算 我和董事会
Mainly the board.
主要是董事会的意见
Anyway, why do you care?
你管这么多干嘛?
No, it's just that people love this stuff.
不是 人们爱这些展品
People, Mr. Daley, love "What's next?"
人们 戴利先生 永远喜新厌旧
You should know that. You left.
这你应该清楚 你不是也走了
My situation changed. My business took off...
我的情况不一样 我的生意刚刚起步
Yeah, you became a success. So would I, if I was a night guard.
对 你成功了 如果我是夜班守卫 我也能
So where are these guys going?
那这些会被运到哪里?
Deep storage. Federal Archives.
联邦档案馆的地下储藏室
- Where's that? - Washington, D.C.
- 在哪儿? - 华盛顿
The Smithsonian.
史密森尼学会
There's got to be something that we can do.
我们可以阻止他们的
It's done! They leave tomorrow morning. It's over.
没用了!它们明天早上就会被运走 都结束了!
Hey, buddy, how you doing? How you doing with all this?
嗨 伙计 你好吗? 你这把老骨头还好吗?
You want what's in here?
想看看我给你带什么了?
You think I got something for you? You think I got a little rope?
猜猜我给你带什么? 是一条绳子吗?
Think you're stronger than me, huh?
你扯得过我吗?
Is that all you got, huh?
你就这点力气吗?
Lawrence! Good to see you, lad!
劳伦斯!很高兴见到你 孩子
Yeah, you too, Teddy.
我也是 泰德!
The Guardian of Brooklyn has returned!
布鲁克林的守护者回来了!
Hey, Ahk. Look, McPhee told me what's going on around here.
嘿 阿克 听着 麦克菲都告诉我了
- I had no idea. - Indeed.
- 我有个主意 - 真的
A lot has transpired, Lawrence, since your last visit. One would say that...
劳伦斯 你最后一次来这儿以后 发生了很多事 俗话说...
- Just... - Cricket.
- 稍等 - 忙人
Hey, Bocephus! Little help over here!
嘿 谁来帮把手!
Hey.
嘿
Hey, fellas. How you doing?
嘿 伙计们 你们好吗?
Well, lookee here.
看看
If it ain't Mr. Big-in-the-Britches himself,
大人物亲自来啦
come back just in time to see us off!
你正好赶上见我们最后一面
Yeah, Jed, I heard. Look, I don't even know how this happened.
杰德 我听说了 听着 我真的不知道事情会变成这样
Yeah. Yeah, real mystery how this happened.
是啊 你当然会觉得很奇怪
Maybe the answer's on that magic buzzing box there in your hand!
也许答案就在你手里那个 嗡嗡作响的盒子里
You weren't here, Gigantor! That's how it happened!
你不在这里了 铁人 所以事情才会变成这样!
Ain't no mystery!
没什么可奇怪的!
The fact is, Larry, there's no one else here to speak on our behalf
事实是 拉瑞 他们开会的时候
during business hours.
没人再为我们说话了
None, none, dum-dum.
没人 没人 笨瓜 笨瓜
Hey, guys! It's okay!
嘿 伙计们!没事的
I'll call the board in the morning, all right? I got some pull now.
我明天一早就给董事会打电话好吗? 我会做弥补
I'll handle this. We're gonna be okay here.
我会处理好 我们都会没事
"We"? Did you hear that? You hear Daydream Johnny?
我们?你听见了吗? 还是我们在做白日梦 强尼?
There ain't been a "we" ever since you put us on the "pay no mind" list.
自从你对我们撒手不管以后 你是你 我们是我们
And that's a cold place to be, boy.
这真让人心寒
Larry, what's done is done.
拉瑞 悲剧已经发生
Even the glory of Rome had to come to an end.
即使辉煌的罗马帝国也有灭亡的一天
Would you please not look dramatically off into the middle distance
你能不能别用这种悲哀的眼神看着空气
when you say that? It makes me feel worse.
你这么说 让我更加痛苦
I don't know what you're talking about.
我不知道你在说些什么
Where are you looking? Where are you looking? I'm over here.
你看什么?你看什么? 我在这里
Just a bit of wall.
我只是在看着墙
Look, guys, maybe it won't be so bad.
听着伙计们 也许事情没那么糟
Yes, you make a good point.
对 你说的对
But this is the Smithsonian we're talking about here.
我们只是要去史密森尼而已
Dexter, you don't know that.
德克斯特 你根本不懂
You're missing the point, Gigantor! They're shipping us out!
重点不是这个 铁人 我们要被扫地出门了!
Larry, I know you're trying to make us feel better.
拉瑞 我知道你只是在安慰我们
I can see that you're genuinely slightly bothered,
我能看得出你在真诚的为我们着急
but it's never going to be the same.
但今天也许是最后一次了
All of us here, together, in this place.
我们所有人 聚在一起 在这里
It ain't never gonna be home, boy.
这里再也不是家了
Jedediah, please! Lawrence, these are emotional times for all of us.
杰迪戴亚 别这样 劳伦斯 这种情况下大家都容易激动
But it is our last night as a family,
但这是我们作为一家人的最后一夜
and I don't want to see it squandered in self-pity.
我不愿意看着你们浪费时间自怨自艾
So who will join me for one final stroll through these hallowed halls?
让我们在这神圣大殿做最后一次游行吧 谁愿意来?
- Do you want to go for a walk? - No.
- 你想去逛一圈吗? - 不
I'm just gonna squander it in self-pity.
我只想自怨自艾
My dear, shall we?
亲爱的 上马吧
Safe journey, my love.
一路平安 亲爱的
Hey, Dexter, want some help there?
嘿 德克斯特 要帮忙吗?
Hey, come on, man. No hard feelings, all right?
别这样伙计 别闹情绪好吗?
It's gonna be fine.
都会过去的
It's almost dawn, Lawrence.
天快亮了 劳伦斯
Yeah. So, where's your crate, Teddy?
是啊 那么 你的木箱呢 泰德?
I won't be making this journey, Lawrence.
我不和他们一起走 劳伦斯
It seems myself, Rexy, and a few of the signature exhibits
我 雷克斯 还有其他一些签名展品
will be staying here for now.
还要留下 暂时
Without the tablet?
可是复活金牌不在了
In truth, Lawrence,
事实上 劳伦斯
Ahkmenrah's tablet will be remaining here with him.
阿卡曼拉的复活金牌 会和他一起留在这里
What?
什么?
They're going without the tablet, my friend.
复活金牌不能随他们一起走了 我的朋友
I'm afraid this night is their last.
这恐怕是他们的最后一夜了
You didn't tell them.
你没告诉他们
Sometimes it's more noble to tell a small lie than deliver a painful truth.
作为一个绅士 痛苦我们只会留给自己
- Are you gonna be okay? - I shall do my best.
- 你会没事吧? - 我会尽力
And who knows?
谁知道呢?
Sometimes the greatest change brings about even greater opportunity.
俗话说 塞翁失马焉知非福
Look at you, Lawrence.
看看你 劳伦斯
You left this place and created quite a life for yourself.
你离开之后 生活发生了翻天覆地的变化
Yeah, I guess so.
是啊 也许你说的对
I should hope you'd do more than guess, my friend.
我的朋友 你要对自己有信心
You're a captain of industry. The world at your fingertips.
你是大企业的老板 一手掌握大权
It seems to me you have everything you wanted.
在我看来 你拥有了一切你想要的
Yeah, no, I know.
没有 我自己知道
No, you don't. If I may, lad,
不 你不懂 如果可以 孩子
allow me to offer you one piece of advice.
请允许我给你一点建议
The key to happiness, to true happiness, is...
获得真正幸福的关键是...
Hang on one sec. I just gotta...
稍等一下 我得...
I got this Japanese deal.
处理一下这宗和日本人的买卖
No, okay, I'm turning this off. I'm sorry.
哦 算了 我关机吧 对不起
The key to happiness?
幸福的关键是?
I'll see you, Teddy.
再见 泰德
(自然历史博物馆)
So they're gone? There's nothing you can do?
他们真的走了? 你什么忙都没帮上?
I wish there was, man. I'm telling you, I tried everything.
我也想做点什么伙计 告诉你 我已经竭尽所能了
I talked to McPhee, I called the board, but they shipped them out this morning.
我和麦克菲谈了 给董事会打了电话 但今早他们还是被运走了
This is a lot of food, Dad.
好多吃的啊 老爸
Yeah. Ed from work's gonna come by. I thought I told you.
对 我公司的爱德今天要过来 我记得我告诉过你
We just have to go over a couple of little work things.
我们要讨论一些工作上的事情
- So you're working tonight. - I used to work every night, remember?
- 那今晚你要工作? - 以前我每晚都工作 记得吗?
That was when you had the coolest job in the world.
那时你拥有全世界最酷的工作
Yeah, well, "cool" doesn't pay for your Guitar God VI or whatever.
但是"酷"可支付不起你昂贵的吉他 和别的花销
- Hello? - Gigantor! It's me, Jedediah!
- 喂? - 铁人! 是我 杰迪戴亚
- Hold! Hold! - Jed?
- 撑住!撑住! - 杰德?
Never surrender!
决不投降!
Jed, what are you... How did you dial the phone?
杰德 你们在干嘛? 你是怎么拨通电话的?
Long story! That brazen little monkey stole the tablet,
说来话长 那个死猴子偷来了复活金牌
and now we're in a world of hurt, boy!
我们这里都打成一片了老兄!
- What's going on? - Kahmunrah!
- 出什么事了? - 卡门拉!
- Kahmunrah? - Ahkmenrah's big brother! He's here!
- 卡门拉? - 阿卡曼拉的哥哥 他来了!
And trust me, not a friendly!
相信我 他是来者不善!
I repeat, not a friendly!
我重复一遍 来者不善!
- Is that Attila, Jed? - I don't know how much longer
- 那是匈奴王的声音吗? 杰德 - 我不知道我们还能撑多久
- we can fight them off! No! - Jed? Are you okay?
- 不要! - 杰德? 你没事吧?
- Let go of me! Help! - Hey, Jed.
- 放开我!救命! - 嘿 杰德
- Let go! No, you let go of me! Help! - Jed?
- 放开我 放开 你放开我 救命啊! - 杰德
What was that about?
怎么了?
I don't know.
我不知道
Here, come on. Gonna drop you off at your mom's.
快点 我要把你送到你妈那儿
- What's going on, Dad? - I'm gonna go find out.
- 出什么事了 老爸? - 我会去弄清楚的
Okay, buddy, McPhee said the Federal Archives are in the Smithsonian.
伙计 麦克菲说联邦档案馆在史密森尼
Where exactly am I going?
那我究竟要去哪里找?
That's the thing, Dad. The Smithsonian is actually 19 different museums.
问得好 老爸 史密森尼其实是19座不同的博物馆
They're laid out around the National Mall,
它们围绕着国家广场
from the Capitol to the Lincoln Memorial.
从国会大厦一直到林肯纪念碑
They got everything there. There's actually some really cool stuff.
那里面什么藏品都有 确实有很多特别酷的东西
Nicky, please focus. Which museum are the Archives in?
尼克 别扯别的 档案馆到底在哪座博物馆里
Not in, under. It looks like it runs underneath the entire Smithsonian.
不是博物馆里 而是地下 它占据了整个史密森尼的地下空间
So if Ahkmenrah's tablet is down there...
那么如果阿卡曼拉的复活金牌在那下面的话
The biggest museum in the world is coming alive.
所有历史人物都将重见天日
What is exactly is your plan here, Dad?
你打算怎么办 老爸?
- Don't worry about it. - You have no plan, do you?
- 这你别担心 - 你根本没有计划是不是?
Now, Nicholas, I have a very good, highly thought-out plan.
尼古拉斯 我有一个超级绝妙的计划
- You have no plan. - Yes, I have no plan.
- 你没有计划 - 好吧 我没有计划
I'll call you when I'm in.
我进去后再联络
Here you go. Thanks.
给你 谢谢
(航天航空馆)
(美国空军)
Welcome to the biggest museum in the world.
欢迎来到全世界最大的博物馆
I know, right? It's a trip.
是啊 这像一场旅行
How about these planes dangling from the ceilings, huh? Pretty weird.
那些挂在天花板上的飞机怎么样? 很神奇吧
Hi, excuse me. Could you tell me how to get to the Federal Archives?
不好意思打扰了 请问联邦档案馆怎么去?
Of course. Just be a historical document worthy of storing for all eternity.
如果你是一个有永久保存价值的档案 就能进去了
I'm kidding. He's not a document.
开个玩笑 他不是档案
I'm sorry, sir, the Archives are underground, and they're a secure area.
抱歉 先生 档案馆在地下层 那里是禁区
Really? Like, totally secure? Okay, thank you.
真的? 完全禁止入内吗? 好吧 谢谢
(非员工请勿进入)
(爱因斯坦摇头公仔)
Ladies and gentlemen, the museum will be closing in one hour.
女士们先生们 博物馆将在一小时后闭馆
(禁止进入 请出示证件)
(卡彭逃漏税被捕)
(卡门拉之门 通往底下世界之门)
Kahmunrah.
卡门拉
Hey! What are you doing?
嘿 你想干嘛?
- No touching. - No, I wasn't gonna touch it.
- 严禁触摸 - 不 我没有想摸
You're moving in with some I.T.T., bro.
你已经产生"摸机"了 伙计
- I.T. T? - That's "Intent to Touch", homey.
- 摸机? - 触摸动机 朋友
No, I wasn't. You're not allowed to go over the...
我没有 我知道这不许碰...
- What, are you gonna kiss it? - All right, sorry.
- 怎么 你还想亲它吗? - 好吧 对不起
Put your hand on it and touch it. 'Cause I stand there
你手放上去碰一下试试 我站在那儿等上一天
and I wait all day for a little girl like you to come in
就是等像你这样想摸它的小女孩
and put her precious nail-polished nails all over the exhibits.
用她带着光鲜亮丽指甲的手碰展品
Sorry. Last time I checked, I thought we lived in a free country, so...
对不起 我以为我们生活在一个自由民主的国家...
- No, we don't. - No?
- 不 不是 - 不是?
It's the United States of Don't Touch That Thing Right in Front of You.
这个国家规定你 不许碰你前面的这个东西
I just want to... I'm allowed to look at it here, okay?
我只是想... 在这儿站着看不犯法吧?
See what happens when you touch it!
你碰一下试试!
So you're threatening me? You're threatening me, Brandon?
你在威胁我吗? 你在威胁我吗 布兰顿
- It's "Brundon." - Excuse me?
- 是布伦顿 - 什么?
- "Brundon"! - "Brundon"?
- 布伦顿 - 布伦顿?
- "Brundon." - "Brundon."
- 布伦顿 - 布伦顿
What, did they run out of U's on your nameplate maker?
好像印你的胸卡时他们丢了个字母
I don't know, did they run out of jokes
不知道 你妈是不是没教过你
at the interesting-joke store that you shop at?
什么时候该开玩笑?
Sorry, it looks like "Brandon", but...
不好意思 看上去像是布兰顿...
I'm not here to be your speech therapist. It's "Brundon"!
我不是来教你语音的 是布伦顿
- "Brundon." Okay... - You never heard of the name before?
- 布伦顿 好的... - 你以前没听说过这名字吗?
"Brundon"? No.
布伦顿?没有
Look up most popular baby names in 1984. "Brundon."
1984年最流行的名字 布伦顿
Okay. Are you threatening me, Brundon?
好吧 你在威胁我吗 布伦顿?
I don't know, Princess Jasmine. Am I?
我不知道 茉莉公主 我有吗?
- Oh, wow. Lunabeam nine-volt. - Yeah.
- 哇 月光九号手电筒 - 没错
Wonderful piece of hardware, huh?
硬件不错啊
- That's their title, Lunabeam Nine. - Great.
- 商标在这儿 月光九号 - 太好了
I prefer the Maglite LED myself, but that's just me.
我个人更偏爱美光手电筒
- Do me a huge favor. - What?
- 帮我个大忙 - 什么忙?
Shove your hands into your pockets, put your attitude way down,
把手放回裤带 放低你的姿态
and, also, be nice to people.
还有 对人友好些
Great. But could I just ask you one thing?
我能再问你一个问题吗?
- Yeah. - Okay, so just to be clear,
- 可以 - 我只想弄清楚
- so, I can't do this, right? - Okay, that's actually crazy.
- 我不能碰它 对吗? - 好吧 你这个疯子
Did you just make a decision to possibly end your life
你想找死吗?
earlier than you were expecting?
你活得不耐烦了吧?
I'm gonna hit you with the flashlight.
我会用手电筒打你
- Now you are threatening me. Okay. - Do not touch it!
- 你在威胁我 - 别碰它!
- Don't touch me. - Do not touch it!
- 别碰我! - 你别碰它!
- Do not touch it! - Don't touch me!
- 别碰它! - 你别碰我!
I'll touch you with my flashlight all day.
我想怎么碰你就怎么碰你
No, your flashlight is meant to illuminate.
不 你的手电筒是用来照明的
I will literally rent a camper,
我打个比方 我们去露营
and we will drive across America with my flashlight on your chest.
开着车横跨美国 一路上我都要拿手电筒碰你
- Don't do that. - Don't do what?
- 你别这样 - 别怎样?
Want to see what happens when I do it one more time?
我就碰了你了怎么样?
- Let's see what happens. - Watch you do nothing.
- 你等着瞧 - 瞧什么瞧
Let's watch you do nothing when I do this.
瞧你傻站在那儿吗
Seriously, Brandon...
说真的 布兰顿...
- Brundon. - Brundon,
- 布伦顿 - 布伦顿
you do not know who you're dealing with.
你知道我是谁吗?
You think you know what it means to be a guard, huh?
你知道当守卫意味着什么吗?
Trust me, you don't know the meaning of the word.
相信我 你根本不懂守卫的含义
I have seen things that you could not imagine.
我见过的东西你连想都不敢想
- Like what kind of stuff? - I'm not gonna tell you.
- 比如什么? - 我不会告诉你
- But you're gonna drop the flashlight... - The way you said it,
- 但是你得放下手电筒... - 你这么说
it sounded like you were gonna say something cool.
听上去你有什么很有意思的事
Yeah, well, you don't get to hear it.
对 可惜你听不到
Drop the flashlight.
放下手电筒
We cool?
没事了吧?
That's actually pretty cool, what you just did.
你刚才真是太酷了
Thank you.
谢谢
No hard feelings?
别记恨我好吗?
- All right? Sorry. - Okay.
- 好吗? 对不起 - 没事
- I'm sorry. - No, It's my fault. I shouldn't have...
- 我很抱歉 - 不 是我的错 我不应该...
No. It takes two opposing forces to cause friction, and...
不 一个巴掌拍不响 再说...
And you're just doing your job, all right.
你只是在尽你的本职 没事的
- Take it easy, man. - Yeah!
- 放松点 伙计 - 好的!
That guy's great.
那家伙真酷
(更衣室)
- Okay, buddy, I'm in. - Great. Where are you?
- 好了 伙计 我进去了 - 太棒了 告诉我你现在的位置
The northeast corridor of the Castle, just off the Commons.
城堡的东北角走廊 刚出国会
- I need you to talk me to the Archives. - Okay.
- 带我到档案馆 - 好的
At the end of the hall, turn right,
到走廊尽头 右转
and there should be a stairwell coming up on your left.
在你左手边可以看到一个楼梯间
- Got it. - Now, it's kind of a maze down there.
- 明白 - 这下面像个迷宫
Those underground tunnels connect a bunch of different buildings.
地下通道把不同建筑连成一体
- It could get complicated. - We'd better hurry,
- 地形非常复杂 - 我们没时间了
we only got 28 minutes till sundown.
还有28分钟太阳就落山了
When you get down to B level, you want to take another left...
下到B层以后 再一次左转
- Nick? Hello? Nick? - Dad! Can you hear...
- 尼克 喂 尼克? - 老爸!听得见吗...
Nick, you're... Nick!
尼克 你说...尼克?
- ID, Brundon. - Hey.
- 身份 布伦顿 - 嘿
- Later, dude. - All right. Yeah.
- 你晚了 老兄 - 是啊
All right. Where are you guys?
好了 大伙儿都在哪儿?
(卡斯特将军)
(阿梅莉亚·埃尔哈特)
(飞越大西洋女飞行员第一人 1937失踪于海洋)
Oh, my God.
哦 上帝
You little troublemaker. I'm gonna deal with you later.
你这个捣蛋鬼 我一会儿再找你算账
No. No! No, no, no!
不 不 不 不 不!
No, English. English, perhaps.
英语 英语会说吗?
I'm sorry, who are you?
抱歉 你是谁?
I am Kahmunrah, the great king of the great kings,
我是卡门拉 我是王中之王
and from the darkest depths of ancient history,
从最黑暗的古老历史深处
I have come back to life!
我死而复生!
Perhaps you did not hear what I just said.
你大概没听清我的话
I am a centuries-old Egyptian Pharaoh. I was dead,
我是古老埃及的法老 我曾经死去
but now I have come back to life!
但是现在 我死而复生!
Yeah, no. I heard that. I got that. Welcome back.
哦 是 我听清了 我明白你的意思 欢迎回来!
- Who are you? - Larry Daley. Daley Devices?
- 你是谁? - 戴利设备的拉瑞·戴利
It's up in New York. It's funny, I know your brother, Ahkmenrah.
我公司在纽约市 很有趣 我还认识你弟弟阿卡曼拉
- Do you? - Yeah.
- 是吗? - 是的
He knows baby brother. The favorite son.
他说他认识我弟弟 最受宠的儿子
- Yeah, good kid. - Isn't he just?
- 对 是个好孩子 - 谁说不是呢?
You know, Mother and Father always gave him the best of everything,
知道吗 妈妈和爸爸总是把所有最好的给他
and I do mean everything. They even gave him the throne.
我说的是所有 甚至包括王位
The throne which was rightfully mine!
我才应该是王位继承人!
- He never mentioned that. - I'll just bet he didn't.
- 他没提过这事 - 我打赌他不会说
Well, now begins the era of Kahmunrah, because I have come back to...
不过卡门拉时代现在来临了 因为我死而复...
Never mind, just hand me the tablet.
算了 把金牌给我
Don't give it to him, Gigantor!
别给他 铁人!
Silence! Silence in there, please!
安静!你们给我安静!
- Don't make me come in there! - No! I won't be muzzled!
- 别逼我进去! - 我不会保持沉默!
Look, that tablet is more powerful
听着 这金牌所拥有的力量
than you, Larry Daley of Daley Devices, can possibly imagine.
是你这个戴利设备的拉瑞·戴利 根本无法想象的
Bringing things back to life is just a parlor trick.
恢复生命只是其中一个小把戏
With it, I shall unlock the Gate to the Underworld
有了它 我就可以开启尘封的地下世界之门
and bring forth my army from the Land of the Dead.
从死亡之地召回我的军队
So, if it's not too much trouble...
如果不麻烦的话...
...hand it over.
...把它给我
Okay, here you go.
好吧 给你
Wise decision.
明智的选择
Yeah, I know. I'm sorry, I thought you wanted the Cube, but...
是啊 很抱歉 我以为你是想要那个魔方 不过...
The Cube?
魔方?
The Cube of Rubik.
魔法立方体
All right, what is this Cube of Rubik, then?
好吧 这个魔法立方体是干什么的?
The Cube. You know, the one that turns all who oppose you to dust?
就是魔方 那个可以把你的敌人化成灰的魔方
That one? Whatever. I thought...
有这个玩意儿吗?随便吧 总之...
It was my bad, 'cause... You know what? By the way,
是我不好 顺便说一句
your brother didn't want to mess with it, either.
你弟弟也不想搞得这么砸
Yeah, he wanted to play it safe, too.
他不想两败俱伤
Just, you sort of struck me as a next-level sort of guy, so I was...
只是 你看上去像比他厉害些 所以我...
I am not my brother, Larry.
我不是我弟弟 拉瑞
I will kill you and your friends in the blink of an eye.
只需一眨眼的功夫 我就能杀光你和你的朋友们
Now take me to this Cube of Rubik.
带我去那个魔法立方体
- Here it is. - Open it.
- 就在这儿 - 打开
Come back here! Come back here with my tablet!
回来!把金牌还给我!
I still have your friends!
你朋友还在我手上!
- Take the wheel! - What?
- 你来开! - 什么?
I said, take the wheel! Oh, we're in it now! I love it! I love it!
我说你来开 打起来了 打起来了 我爱它
Just keep her straight, I'll handle the rest.
笔直往前 其他我来对付
Now, charge!
前进!
- Okay, so what's the plan here? - We're Americans! We don't plan, we do!
- 好吧 你有什么计划? - 我们是美国人 不计划 只做
Now hold on!
不要减速!
See that? Act first, think later! Works every time!
看到没有?先行而后思 每次都管用!
You're in good hands!
我可是好手!
General George A. Custer of the Fighting U.S. 7th Cavalry,
美国第七骑兵队将军 乔治·阿姆斯特朗·卡斯特
at your service.
为您效劳
I'm good, I'm good! Fly, you fool!
我没事 继续开 笨蛋
What's the rumpus, ace?
你们吵什么吵 牛仔?
Look, lady, could you get out of the way?
听着 女士 你能让开吗?
Lady? Who are you calling lady? The name is Amelia.
女士? 你叫谁女士? 我是阿梅莉亚
Amelia Earhart! Perhaps you've heard of me?
阿梅莉亚·埃尔哈特 我想你听说过我吧
Oh, right. You're a famous pilot or whatever.
哦 是啊 著名飞行员什么的吧
Pilot? I was the first woman to fly the Atlantic!
飞行员? 我可是第一个飞越大西洋的女性
First woman to receive the Flying Cross,
第一个荣获飞行十字勋章的女性
first woman to fly across the 48 states in a gyroprop.
第一个驾驶自转旋翼机 飞越美国48个州的女飞行员
Now if you'd wipe that perhaps-permanent look of alarm off your kisser,
如果你愿意的话请先放下 你那副永远紧张兮兮的嘴脸
I was wondering if you might be so kind as to tell me exactly where I am.
请告诉我我现在在哪儿 非常感谢
You're in a museum. Or, actually, under it.
你在一个博物馆 准确点是博物馆下面
And I'm in kind of a dangerous situation right now,
我现在是众矢之的
so you might not want to be anywhere near me.
所以你最好躲到离我远点的地方
- Wow, you're fast. - What's your name, flyboy?
- 你动作真快 - 你叫什么 飞行员?
My name is Larry Daley.
我叫拉瑞·戴利
Well, Larry Daley, in case you weren't listening,
拉瑞·戴利 你给我听好了
I'm not one to shy away from danger.
我可不是个胆小怕事的人
How about spears? Are you one to shy away from spears?
那矛呢 你怕不怕矛呢?
Let's ankle, skipper! Now we're gonna have some fun.
让我们找点乐子 机长! 痛快玩一场吧
Ninety-eight, ninety-nine, bingo!
98 99 完美
Like a Golden Fleece.
像金羊毛一样
All right, troops, when your enemies captured me,
听着 士兵们 当你们的敌人抓住我的时候
they made themselves my enemies as well.
他们也就成了我的瓮中之鳖
Big mistake. Big mistake.
大错误 一个大错误
All right, here's the plan.
我的计划是这样的
On the third bugle blast, I shall loudly announce, "Attack!"
吹响三声号角 我会大声宣布: "攻击!"
At which point, we will all jump out of this box
然后我们全体跳出这个箱子
and attack.
开始攻击
Mind bomb. What do you think?
很震撼吧 觉得怎么样?
You, Sacaja...
你说 萨什么什么...
That is not my name.
那不是我的名字
- Sacajamea. - No.
- 萨卡娅米尔 - 不是
- Sack-in-a-box. - No.
- 娘娘腔 - 不是
- Cinco de Mayo. - I know you are a famous general...
- 死亡节日 - 我知道你是个著名的将军...
That's all right, that's all right. I'm a person, just like you.
那算不上什么 我也是个普通人 和你一样
But won't yelling, "Attack!" Alert the enemy
当你大叫"攻击"的时候
that we are about to attack?
敌人不就立刻知道我们要攻击了吗?
What?
什么?
Yeah, I guess so.
哦 也许你说的对
You're quite the popular fellow, Mr. Daley.
你很受欢迎嘛 戴利先生
Why don't you just skedaddle?
你干嘛不直接逃走?
I can't skedaddle. My friends are being held down there.
我不能逃 我的朋友还在他们手上
I got to go get them. I got to find another way down.
我得去救他们 得另找一条路下去
This is new.
以前没见过
Hey, it's all right. I don't want to hurt you.
没事 我不会伤害你们
I don't think it's you they're afraid of, Mr. Daley.
我想他们怕的不是你 戴利先生
Trade you. Thanks.
交换 谢谢
Back off! Just back off!
退后 给我退后!
I will fork you!
小心被我叉到
How about you, huh?
别轻举妄动
Never send a boy to do a woman's job.
男人就是不如女人
I spent two weeks spear-hunting with a tribe in Micronesia.
我曾经用两周的时间 在密克罗尼西亚群岛和土著学习用矛
The Micronesians had much slower reflexes.
密克罗尼西亚人的反应没这么快
Come on!
走
It's over! It's over! It's all over!
战争结束了!战争结束了!
Well, this is one humdinger of a hootenanny.
这儿可真是热闹啊
Excuse me. Sorry. Excuse me.
让一下 不好意思 让一让
Wow, four bars in 1945.
哇 1945年的信号这么强
- Hello? - Dad, finally!
- 喂? - 老爸 总算通了!
I've been studying these plans to the Archives.
我一直在研究档案馆地形
Looks like once you get down the stairwell...
一旦你下了楼梯...
Oh, I'm way past the stairwell, Nicky.
哦 我早就下了楼梯了 尼克
- So you found everyone? - Sort of.
- 这么说你找到大家了? - 算是吧
What is that flibberty-widget you are talking to?
你在对着什么东西讲话?
- Who's that? - It's Amelia Earhart.
- 那是谁? - 阿梅莉亚·埃尔哈特
You found Amelia Earhart?
你找到了阿梅莉亚·埃尔哈特?
I... Hey!
我...嘿!
- Wait a minute! - Buddy, what's your hurry?
- 等会儿! - 老兄 你急什么啊!
- Didn't you hear? The war's over! - Sorry. These guys are chasing me.
- 你没听到吗? 战争结束啦! - 抱歉 那些人在追我
What? What am I looking at, Mardi Gras?
什么?都是些什么人啊 狂欢节表演吗?
- What unit are you from? - I'm from Brooklyn.
- 你是哪里来的? - 布鲁克林
What? Are you serious? I'm from Flatbush! Hey, fellas!
你说真的? 我是弗莱巴许的 嘿 兄弟们
These so-and-so's are trying to rough up my pal here
那些怪人要打我兄弟
just 'cause he's from Brooklyn!
就因为他是布鲁克林的
- Thank you! - You got it! Fight!
- 谢谢 - 别客气 给我打!
Hey, mister! You forgot your...
嘿 先生!你忘了东西...
What the heck is this thing?
这是什么玩意儿? （请注意片尾曲中有相关情节）
Excuse me. Mind if I get in here?
对不起 把她借我一会儿行吗?
Any time you're done, Mr. Daley.
你吻完没有 戴利先生
- Call me! - Thank you for that.
- 给我打电话! - 谢谢你
So you're quite the smooth operator, aren't you, Mr. Daley?
你对付女人挺有一套啊 戴利先生
Quick!
快!
- That actually worked. - What's next?
- 终于挡住了 - 接下去干嘛?
Look, nothing personal, but I'm kind of in the middle of something here
听着 我不是针对你 不过我现在正处于水深火热中
that's not really your fight.
这可不是你开飞机这么简单
It's because I'm a woman, isn't it?
就因为我是个女人 对不对?
No, it's because I've got this ancient raised-from-the-dead evil Pharaoh guy
不 因为有个死而复生的邪恶法老
who's willing to kill me and probably anyone near me to get this tablet
要我手上这块石板 他会杀了我甚至我身边的任何一个人
so he can rule the world.
有了石板他就能统治世界
So it is because I'm a woman!
所以说还是因为我是女人!
- Look, I... - No, you look, Mr. Daley!
- 听着 我... - 不 你给我听着 戴利先生!
If it weren't for me, you'd still be lost in that monochromatic mayhem!
要不是我把你拉出来了 你现在还陷在那个黑白闹剧中
- Lost in what? - Black and white photo, you boob!
- 陷在什么中? - 那张黑白照片 蠢货
Now listen, and listen good. I can help you.
听着 听好了 我想帮你
I want to help you, and not because I like you, which so far I don't,
我想帮你 不是因为我喜欢你 我才不喜欢你
but because I smell adventure, and, damn it, I want in.
而是因为我闻到了冒险的味道 见鬼 我要加入你
Okay. Don't blame me if something happens to you.
好吧 出了事可别怪我
I should be so lucky.
我的命长着呢
I am Kahmunrah. I am half god,
我是卡门拉 我是半个神
once removed on my mother's side,
从我出生开始
rightful ruler of Egypt, future ruler of...
我就是埃及王国的合法继承人 将来也要统治...
Well, everything else.
所有一切
Now, I have lost some men.
我损失了一些人
So, I am in need of some new generals to join me in my little plan
所以现在我需要一些帮手
of conquering this world.
和我一起征服世界
Ivan the Terrible.
恐怖的伊凡
Napoleon Bonaparte.
拿破仑·波拿巴
And young Al Capone.
还有年轻的艾尔·卡彭
Yeah.
是
Some of the most despicable, most feared leaders in all of history.
你们都是历史上数一数二的大坏蛋
Gentlemen,
先生们
really, it's just fantastic to meet you all.
真的 我真想不到能见到你们
- And us, too. - And me, you.
- 我们也是 - 我也是
All I ask is your allegiance, and in return, I offer you the world.
只要你们衷心于我 我承诺你们的是整个世界
Literally. Are there any questions?
你们有什么问题吗?
Yeah, I got one. How come you're wearing a dress?
我有一个问题 你怎么会穿着裙子?
This is not a dress. This is a tunic.
这不是裙子 这叫做袍子
It was the height of fashion 3,000 years ago, I assure you.
3000年前很流行的 我告诉你
Are there any other questions?
还有别的问题吗?
Da. This dress you're wearing,
有 你穿的这个裙子
do we have to wear one of these, too?
我们也要穿吗?
Were you not listening? I just told Mr. Capone here
你刚才没在听吗? 我已经回答了卡彭先生的问题
that this is not a dress.
这不是裙子
It is, in fact, a tunic. Very big difference.
事实上 这是件袍子 区别很大的
Are there any other questions?
还有问题吗?
Any questions not about the dress?
还有别的与裙子无关的问题吗?
Tunic?
袍子
All right, then. Moonlight is wasting,
那么好吧 不要浪费月色了
- and the time is short. - Short?
- 我们时间很短 - 短?
Why do you look at me when you say "short"?
为什么你说"短"的时候要看着我?
Sorry. It slipped out.
对不起 我无意的
Da. If we are talking about world domination,
好吧 如果你说的是征服世界
then of course, I am interested.
那我当然有兴趣
But first I want to clarify something so you know what you are getting.
不过我想先澄清一件事情 你得搞清楚你在和谁合作
People always say, "Ivan the Terrible, he's so terrible.
人们总是说: 伊凡很恐怖 他很吓人
"I'm so scared of Ivan. He's bad news."
我很怕伊凡 他是个恶棍
When in fact, the correct translation is
其实正确的翻译应该是
"Ivan the Awesome".
令人畏惧的伊凡
Ivan the Awesome?
令人畏惧的伊凡?
It's not really as catchy, is it?
那个比较难记 不是吗?
I mean, "Ivan the Terrible", that really pops.
我是说 恐怖的伊凡更容易记
But I wasn't terrible. In fact, I was quite an effective leader.
可是我一点都不恐怖 事实上我是个很能干的领袖
Duly noted. Now, I'd like to wrap up the old meet-and-greet
好我记住了 现在我想用一个问题来结束
by asking you gentlemen a question.
今晚的面谈会
Are you with me?
你们跟不跟我?
- Yeah. Yeah, sure. - Oui.
- 跟 跟 - 跟
- Da, but... - Then bring Larry Daley of Daley Devices
- 我跟 不过... - 那就把戴利设备的拉瑞·戴利
and the Golden Tablet of Ahkmenrah to me!
还有阿卡曼拉的复活金牌弄来给我!
We'll get you back down to your chums, Mr. Daley.
我带你下去找你的朋友 戴利先生
You won't get lost following Amelia Earhart.
跟着阿梅莉亚·埃尔哈特 你绝对不会迷路
Quick, get down.
快点 蹲下
Well, well, Mr. Daley, I quite like the way you're holding me.
戴利先生 我很喜欢你这么搂着我
No. Sorry, I wasn't trying to...
对不起 我不是那个意思...
Oh, please, stop beating your gums, Mr. Daley.
拜托你戴利先生 别嘟嘟囔囔的
You haven't been able to take your cheaters off my chassis
自打你看到我那刻起
since the moment we met.
你的眼睛就没离开过我的飞机底盘
I literally didn't understand one word of that.
你说的话我全部听不懂
Is it just me or is there music in the air?
是我听错了还是有人在唱歌?
∮ ... my baby, we can make it shine We can take forever... ∮
∮ ...宝贝 我们可以将它照耀 我们可以永远... ∮
You! Little flying angel things! Quiet!
你们 会飞的小天使 安静!
They're cupids, Mr. Daley. Gods of love.
他们是丘比特 戴利先生 是爱神
Great. Gods of love, would you shut up? Please shut up. We're trying to hide.
太棒了 爱神 你们能闭嘴吗? 闭嘴 我们会暴露的
∮ Yeah! More than a woman! Yeah! ∮
∮ 耶 特别的女人 耶 ∮
No, don't change the arrangement, it's not about the arrangement. Quiet!
别换了 不是编曲的问题 给我安静!
Kick the chorus, y'all!
大家一起唱!
∮ More than a woman ∮
∮ 特别的女人 ∮
Yo, show me what you got, night guard!
让我看看你的能耐 守卫!
All right, come on. Let's go.
快点 我们走
∮ More than a woman to me ∮
∮ 对我来说是个特别的女人 ∮
∮ More than a woman ∮
∮ 特别的女人 ∮
∮ She's more than a woman ∮
∮ 她是个特别的女人 ∮
And so, the little tiny man who could not be a smaller or shorter mouse
你这只小到不能再小的小老鼠
runs into the claws of the giant cat!
自动跑到大猫咪的面前
You're really hung up on the height, aren't you?
你真的这么在乎高度啊
- No, it's not about height, see... - Yes, you are.
- 我根本不在乎高度... - 不 你在乎
You're saying I'm a little mouse, you're a giant cat.
你的意思是我只是一只小老鼠 而你是一只大猫咪
- I am the giant cat. - No offense, I just...
- 我是大猫咪 - 我并不想冒犯你 不过...
You're Napoleon. There's a complex named after you.
你是拿破仑 你拥有很多很多的形容词
You're famous for being little, and it's true. Look.
矮就是其中之一 真的 你自己看看
Oh, you naive American man-boy.
哦 你这个幼稚的美国男孩
Look. Neither of us are gonna be jamming anytime soon, right?
听着 现在讨论这个很无聊好吗
So it's not like we should... It's not even an issue.
我们不该浪费时间... 在这个不值一提的问题上
It's not about height or something else. It's a plan. It's a brilliant plan.
人不是以高矮来评价的 是头脑 一个伟大的头脑
- So it was a plan. - Snazzy maneuver, Emperor.
- 你是很有头脑 - 说的好 皇帝先生
Merci, mademoiselle.
谢谢 小姐
Now, if your boyfriend would kindly come with me...
如果你的男朋友能合作点 跟我走...
I'm not her boyfriend.
我不是她男朋友
- Not her boyfriend. - No.
- 不是男朋友 - 不是
Just friends?
普通朋友?
- Yeah, friends. - Acquaintances. Friends.
- 是 普通朋友 - 只是认识而已 普通朋友
Were you guys, like, friends in college
你们的关系 是不是类似那种大学同学
and just afraid now to both ruin your relationship
相互暗恋 想要更进一步发展
by telling the other person that you want to be more than friends,
但却不敢告诉对方
that you like-like each other?
怕毁了你们现在的关系?
One more time? I'm sorry. I didn't catch the...
再说一遍好吗 抱歉 我没听明白...
Were you guys, like, friends in college
你们的关系 是不是类似那种大学同学
and now both afraid to ruin your relationship
相互暗恋 想更进一步发展
by telling the other person that you want to be more than friends,
但却不敢告诉对方
that you like-like each other?
怕毁了你们现在的关系?
- No. - No?
- 不是 - 不是?
I just love the nitty-gritty of relationships. All us French do.
我喜欢挖掘两性关系的本质 这是法国人的爱好
- Great. - Yes. Amour!
- 太好了 - 是啊 爱情
Now.
行了
- This way, or you die. - Yes.
- 跟我走 要不就杀了你 - 遵命
- Wait, I'm coming with you! - No! Our fight is not with you.
- 等等 我也去 - 不! 这事与你无关
- so you gotta bet a second time. - All right. Okay.
- 你还得再下一次注 - 好 好吧
My hair is currency in certain parts of Europe.
我的发型在欧洲一带流通很广
It's true. Currency, like gold or paper money.
真的 流通很广 就像黄金和钱
The Duomo was purchased with just one locket.
一小盒能买下整个大教堂
Listen up, kemosabe.
听着 朋友
This rodeo clown wouldn't know a flapjack from a flyswatter.
这个马戏团小丑 连煎饼和苍蝇拍都分不清
Now, Gigantor's out there risking his hide for us.
现在铁人正在外面为我们拼命
The least we can do is give him some help.
至少我们要帮他一把
Some big help. But we can't very well do that if we're stuck in here, now, can we?
我们能帮大忙 但是在这里坐以待毙就什么忙也帮不上
We need to escape.
我们得逃出去
What's a flapjack?
煎饼是什么东西?
It's like a biscuit or a scone.
类似一种饼干或者面包的东西
- Chest bump? - Yeah.
- 碰胸 - 好的
Then deadly. Watch.
你玩完了 看牌
Guard your cards, okay? Now you bet.
看好你的牌 现在下注吧
Okay, now you got to throw some cards down.
现在你得丢点牌下来
- Ready? - Ready.
- 准备好了? - 准备好了
Say something. Say anything. This is no fun. You're supposed to...
说点什么 说点什么 这不好玩 你必须...
- Hey! What are you two doing out here? - Octavius, go!
- 嘿 你们俩想干嘛? - 奥克塔维厄斯 跑!
- You, make a run for it, I'll hold them off! - I will not leave you!
- 你 快跑 我掩护你 - 我不会一个人跑的
Ain't no time for your Roman melodrama! Now, get! Go!
现在不是演罗马连续剧 快跑 马上!
Old Jedediah will be fine.
老杰迪戴亚不会有事
Now, you're in real trouble.
好了 你麻烦大了
Why, these aren't real rubies at all.
这些根本不是真的红宝石
Ruby slippers indeed.
真品红宝石鞋
But, whoever you are, Archie Bunker, you had one comfortable throne.
虽然不知道这个阿奇·巴克是谁 但这椅子坐的可真舒服
Hey, boss.
老大
Caught this one trying to escape through a rust hole in the crate.
这家伙从箱子的一个锈洞里逃出来 给我们抓住了
One of his little friends got away.
还有一个跑了
Oh, please. What damage could they possibly do?
拜托 他们能干得了什么?
Why, they're no bigger than a little grain of couscous. Aren't you?
看看 他们小的好像一粒米 是不是?
You know, two words come to mind when I hear you talk.
听你说话我想到了两个词
"Delusional" and "weirdo".
神经病 精神分裂
And if I had to say a third, "goofy". Just goofy.
如果还要说第三个词的话 那就是"蠢猪"
Now you let old Jedediah out of here or he's gonna get angry.
你快把老杰迪戴亚放出来 不然他可要发火了
Well played, Jedediah!
说的好 杰迪戴亚
I'm sorry, I can't take you seriously. You're just adorable,
对不起 我实在认真不起来 你太可爱了
even when you're threatening me. It's hilarious.
连你威胁我的样子也有趣极了
Is it just me, or are these guys unbelievably cute?
是我的问题 还是这些小家伙真是可爱的要命
Now hold it a second, now.
你给我省省吧
Now, you have a right to keep me as your captive, torture me, even,
你可以囚禁我 甚至折磨我
but don't call me cute! I ain't cute!
但不许说我可爱 我不可爱!
Steady, my friend! Just stay alive! I will find you!
撑住 我的朋友! 坚持住 我会救你出去!
Gigantor. No!
铁人 不!
Hello, Mr. Daley. Nice to see you again.
你好 戴利先生 很高兴再一次见到你
Now, if you don't mind, I shall take that from you.
如果你不介意的话 这个我要拿走了
Thank you.
谢谢
Finally. Finally! After 3,000 years,
终于!过了整整3000年
my evil army of the damned, my beautiful, beautiful army,
我被诅咒的黑暗军团 我可爱的军团
shall be unleashed!
将重见天日!
I'm afraid that Mother and Father may have
我恐怕妈妈和爸爸
slightly changed the combination on me.
背着我稍稍改了一下密码
I guess this whole unleashing-the-underworld thing
这么说地下怪物重见天日这套
isn't really working out for you, huh?
行不通了 对吧?
It must be really frustrating, 'cause you've waited thousands of years
你一定很难过吧 毕竟你都等了几千年了
to come back from the dead and everything,
好不容易死而复生
and now you can't get it open.
却打不开地狱之门
Fear not, for I shall wait a thousand more if I must.
我不怕 有必要的话我还可以再等上一千年
Good, 'cause in a few hours you'll be standing here in a frustrated position,
很好 不过再过几个小时你就会 变成一尊沮丧的雕塑
frozen, and I'll walk out of here with my buddies and that'll be that.
冻在那里 而我可以带着我的朋友们 离开这里
So, I got all night.
所以 我不介意等上一整晚
Really? All night? Well!
真的吗?一整晚?
He doesn't.
他等不了
Open that cage.
打开笼子
- What are you doing? - No touching! No touching!
- 你干嘛? - 不许碰我!不许碰我!
Don't you manhandle me!
你敢对我动粗试试
- Look, he's having a little tantrum. - Jed?
- 看呐 小家伙生气了 - 杰德?
Don't you squirm! Don't squirm. It'll only be worse for you.
别动 别动 不然你会更难受
- Put him down! - Don't be afraid.
- 放开他! - 别害怕
I shan't hurt you.
我不会伤害你的
I lied.
我骗你了
I don't think he has all night at all, Mr. Daley.
我想他可等不了一整晚 戴利先生
From the looks of things, I'd say he has a little over an hour.
看这速度 他只剩不到一个小时了
Take me out of here!
放我出去!
You were the guardian! You know all about this tablet.
你是守卫! 你很了解这块复活金牌
You're obviously much more clever than the rest of us.
而你看上去也比我们这里所有人都聪明
You may or may not know the combination,
不管你知道还是不知道密码
but I am going to give you exactly one hour to figure it out.
我给你一个小时的时间去想
If you do not, I shall kill your friends.
到时间不给我密码 我就杀光你的朋友
And please don't think about escaping, for I shall be watching you.
还有你别想溜 我会监视你的行动
Look, I don't even know how to begin
听着 我根本无从下手
to decipher this thing, all right? Really.
我完全不懂怎么破译密码 真的
What a pity.
太可惜了
And your little cowboy friend seemed like such a charming little fellow.
你的牛仔小朋友看上去那么惹人喜欢
Ah, well. Tick-tock, Mr. Daley. Your hour has begun.
时间在走哦 戴利先生 轮到你行动了
Hey! You got this, partner. I know you do.
我挺你 伙计 我知道你行的
You got this!
我挺你!
There you are! Are you all right? I've been worried sick! Sick I tell you.
你来了!你还好吗? 我都快担心死了!
- No, I'm fine. - So what's our next move, partner?
- 我没事 - 下一步计划是什么 拍档?
I don't know. I just got to get this tablet translated.
我也不知道 我必须先破译密码
Oh, great! This guy again.
哦好极了 又是这家伙!
Look, buddy, we don't want any trouble, all right?
听着伙计 我不想惹麻烦好吗?
Look at that!
看呐
I guess our sassy cephalopod was just a fish who didn't like being out of water.
看来章鱼先生只是太缺水了 它也只条普通的鱼类
He's not such a ballywagger after all.
看上去也没那么讨厌嘛
Okay. Glad you're happy.
好 知道你很高兴
Hello? A little assistance?
喂 帮个忙好吗?
Hey, Teddy! Perfect!
嘿 泰德 太好了
Maybe you could help us.
也许你能帮我们
I'd love to help you, but first things first.
我很愿意帮忙 但先帮我解决我的燃眉之急
My nose is so itchy, it's driving me insane.
鼻子痒的我快疯掉了
I hate to ask, but, as you see, I'm missing a few body parts.
我知道这很无礼 不过我看上去有点缺胳膊少腿
- Could you please give us a scratch? - Yeah, sure.
- 可以帮我挠一下吗? - 当然可以
Oh, yes! That's exquisite. A little over there...
哦 对是这里 再过去一点...
- Yes! - More?
- 太棒了! - 还要?
Oh, yes! Yes! Oh, that's...
哦 是的 是的...
Sweet rutabaga pie, that was divine.
终于舒服了
Theodore Roosevelt, at your service.
西奥多·罗斯福很高兴为你效劳
Twenty-sixth President of the United States, Rough Rider,
这是美国第二十六届总统 狂野骑士
founder of the national parks, and a whole bunch of other stuff.
他建造了国家公园 还有很多别的
- Have we met? - No, there's another Teddy.
- 我们认识吗? - 不 还有另一个泰德
- We have one of you in New York. - Really? What's he like, this other me?
- 纽约博物馆也有一个你 - 真的? 长什么样? 像我一样?
He's pretty much the same, except with...
差不多 只是...
Except what? Say it. Except with a body?
只是什么?只是他多了个身体?
- Yes. He has a body. - Oh, dash it, the pain!
- 是 他有身体 - 哦 见鬼 你刺激到我了
- And a horse. - Excuse me!
- 还有一匹马 - 打断一下
We really need someone to translate what's written on this tablet.
我们需要翻译这块石板上的文字
- Do you read hieroglyphics? - Yes, I do, missy.
- 你看得懂象形文字吗? - 是 我懂 小姐
That's a simple one.
这很简单
Bird. Man with spear. Sideways fish. Beetle. Vase.
鸟 拿矛的人 斜过来的鱼 甲虫 花瓶
Okay, and what does that mean?
那这代表什么?
It means, and this is just a rough translation,
我只是粗略的翻译一下
"A man with a spear trapped a bird and a sideways fish in a vase.
一个拿矛的男人在一个花瓶里 抓住了一只鸟和一条斜过来的鱼
"And there was also a beetle."
还有一只甲虫
- I don't think that's it. - That's just one possible translation.
- 我想你是胡说八道 - 那只是其中一种译法
Another possible translation is,
另一种译法是
"You will find the combination you seek
只要能解开法老墓穴深处的秘密
"if you figure out the secret at the heart of Pharaoh's tomb."
你就能破译密码
- Okay, and what does that mean? - I don't know! What am I, the Sphinx?
- 好吧 这是什么意思? - 不知道 我又不是狮身人面像
"What's this? What's that?" Why don't you ask New York Teddy?
"这是什么" "那是什么" 你们怎么不去问纽约那个泰德
I'm sure he'd love to get his grabby little fingers all over that thing!
我打赌他会拿他贪婪的双手摸遍这块东西
Probably let his horse lick it, too!
可能还会让他的马舔两下!
Mr. Daley, we should be going to the sculpture gallery.
戴利先生 我们应该去雕塑馆
I think there's someone there who might have a better thought on this.
那儿有个人也许真的能帮助我们
The fellow we're looking for is just down here.
我们要找的人就在这里
- Bonsoir. - Hello, young lady.
- 晚上好 - 你好 年轻人
Hey, excuse me. Could we keep moving, please?
嘿 抱歉 能快点走吗?
We certainly could, but then we might miss a rare opportunity.
当然可以 但我不想错过这么好的机会
I mean, she is a Degas, Mr. Daley.
这可是德加的作品 戴利先生
Okay, it's just I got a little buddy stuck in an hourglass,
我的小朋友被困在沙漏里
I got a pitch meeting at Wal-Mart in the morning...
明天一早我还有个棘手的会议 对方是沃尔玛...
- It would be great if we could... - He's right here.
- 请快点好吗... - 他就在这儿
I think he'll have a thought on this.
我认为他肯定知道什么
Mr. Thinker, we're sorry to interrupt your contemplation,
思想者先生 抱歉打断你的沉思
but we really need to figure out the secret at the heart of Pharaoh's tomb.
我们想知道法老墓穴深处的秘密
I'm thinking. I'm thinking.
我在思考 我在思考
I'm thinking.
我在思考
- I'm thinking. - It's not happening with him.
- 我在思考 - 问他没用
Oh, wow.
哦 哇哦
You've gotta be kidding me. Check that out!
没开玩笑吧 看看!
Hey! Hey!
嘿 嘿
Buddy! Over here! This is serious.
伙计 看这儿! 这很要紧!
Apparently, it's a matter of life and death.
对 生死攸关
I'll tell you what's a matter of life and death.
让我告诉你什么叫生死攸关
That beautiful lady over there.
看到那个美女吗
Hey, baby! Check out the gun show going on over here!
嘿宝贝 看看我的肌肉秀
Firepower!
猛男!
He's certainly no Einstein.
看来他没爱因斯坦那种脑子
- Biceps! Deltoids... - Yeah.
- 二头肌!三角肌... - 对了
- Wait a minute. I saw a bunch of those. - A bunch of whats?
- 等等 我见过一堆那个 - 一堆什么?
- Little Einsteins. - Where?
- 小爱因斯坦 - 在哪儿?
Over there, in Air and Space.
在航天航空馆
I gotta get over there.
得马上过去
What?
怎么了?
- Nothing. - Okay. Then why are you staring at me?
- 没什么 - 那你这么盯着我干嘛?
I don't wanna miss a moment.
我不想浪费一秒钟
All right, good, but we should get going, 'cause we...
好的 很好 不过我们得快点 因为...
- Why? - You talk too much, ace.
- 干什么? - 你太啰嗦了 牛仔
I don't know why I did that, Mr. Daley.
我也不知道我为什么吻你 戴利先生
I just feel as if I've been asleep for a long time and now, suddenly,
我只觉得我好像沉睡了很久很久
I'm awake.
突然之间 我醒了
I can explain that...
我可以解释...
But really, I could. I really...
真的 我可以解释...
Again, why?
又打我 为什么?
Great, you're back.
太好了 你们又回来了
Okay. Yeah. Great.
好吧 唱得好
Love theme from Titanic. Good, but not really appropriate.
泰坦尼克的主题曲 唱得很好 谢谢你们帮倒忙
You don't let yourself enjoy things much, do you, Mr. Daley?
你就不会享受人生吗 戴利先生?
Okay, you know what? It's not really the song choice.
听着 不是你们选错歌了 好吗?
And by the way, you're a little pitchy.
还有 你们真的很烦人
Well, I thought you were amazing, and you look wonderful.
我觉得你们很棒 可爱极了
Could you just fly away, please?
飞远点 好吗?
And so the adventure continues.
冒险继续
What did I tell you? Enough!
叫你们别吵了 聋了吗?
You know, I do sort of feel like a floating butterfly.
知道吗 我感觉自己 像只翩翩起舞的蝴蝶
You are crazier than a road lizard.
你像只臭蜥蜴
Mr. Egypt, these two here heard that we're taking over the world
埃及先生 这两个人听说我们要征服世界
and they want in. I don't know who they are,
他们想加入 虽然我不认识他们
but they're on exhibit here, too, apparently.
但他们也是这里的展品
I don't even know what they are.
他们到底是什么东西
I'm sorry, but we're all full up in our axis of evil today. Sorry.
对不起 我们这儿坏人的名额满了
Come on! But I'm bad! I'm bad!
别呀!我很坏 我真的很坏
Hey, I could show you how bad I am!
让你看看我有多坏
Fear me!
怕我吗
I'm sorry. I'm just not buying it.
对不起 我没被吓到
You don't seem very bad. You just seem sort of vaguely grouchy to me.
你看上去不坏 只是脾气有点差而已
Oh, boy.
哦 上帝
What are you doing? What is that? What is this?
你在干嘛?这是什么?这是什么?
What does it mean? You've lost me.
这是什么意思?我搞不懂了
Is that you breathing? Because I can't hear myself think.
这是你呼吸的声音吗? 吵得我都快不能思考了
Can I make one suggestion to you, my friend? Just simplify.
让我给你一个建议吧 朋友 别再添乱了
There's just too much going on here.
这里已经够乱的了
You're evil, you're asthmatic, you're a robot... And what is the cape for?
你很邪恶 你有哮喘 你是个机器人 还有你这斗篷是干嘛的?
Are we going to the opera? I don't think so.
我们这儿又不是在演话剧
Sorry! Goodbye.
不好意思!再见
Attention!
有情况!
He's leaving with the tablet!
他带着金牌逃了
Where?
哪里?
Give me that.
让我看
He's not trying to figure out the... He's trying to escape!
他不是在想密码 他要逃跑!
Go. Go! All of you! Kill him! And bring me that tablet.
所有人给我追 杀了他! 把金牌带回来给我
Come on, people! Let's go! Without that tablet, we've nothing!
行动起来 快 金牌是我们一切的希望
Streltsy! Go!
士兵们 上!
Thought you could get away, didn't you, Larry Daley?
你逃不出我的手掌 拉瑞·戴利
Criminy, we're jimmy-jacked.
老天 我们玩完了
- Jimmy-jacked? Really? - It's the way I speak.
- 玩完了? 是吗? - 我就是这么说话的
Yeah, I know, but that one sounds made up, even for you.
我明白你的意思 就是听上去有点奇怪
"Oh, no, our path has been blocked by bad people." What's the fun in that?
"不 不 我们的路被坏人堵住了" 这么说还有什么意思?
The point is, we're not getting into the Air and Space right now.
问题是我们现在去不了航天航空馆了
- You're right. We are jimmy-jacked. - Jimmy-jacked.
- 你说的对 我们玩完了 - 玩完了
Come on.
快
They say a good man rules this union.
他们都说那个总统是个好人
I promised Jedediah I would bring help,
我答应过杰迪戴亚我会找人帮忙
and help I will bring.
我一定会找到
Charge!
进攻!
Misjudged the distance.
低估这段距离了
Who's there?
谁?
Jupiter, protect me.
朱庇特神 求你护佑我
Remain very still.
一动不动
They can sense movement.
他们对移动很敏感
Apparently, they can also hear me talking to myself.
显然 他们也能听到我自言自语
I'm not a nut.
我不是坚果
No!
不要!
We should be okay in here for a while.
在这里躲一会儿吧
So, how long have you guarded antiquities?
你当守卫多久了?
What? Oh, no, I don't actually work at the...
什么?哦 其实我不在这儿工作...
I just thought with the fancy getup and all...
你的装备看上去很齐全 所以我以为...
No, I borrowed this.
这是我借的
I mean, I was a guard back in New York, but that was a while ago.
我在纽约确实当过守卫 那是很久以前了
So why did you leave? Did you not enjoy it?
为什么不干了?不喜欢了吗?
No, I loved it. I just...
不 我爱这份工作 只是...
Things sort of took off in a different direction, so...
人生往另一个方向在发展 所以...
- So what do you do now? - Well, I sort of...
- 那你现在的工作是什么? - 怎么说呢...
Well, I sort of design products and sell them.
我发明产品然后销售出去
- You're an inventor! - I am.
- 你是发明家! - 是的
I am an inventor, yeah. I invent stuff.
我是个发明家 发明东西
Like the rocket ship?
比如火箭?
- No. - The sea plane.
- 不是 - 水上飞机?
- The dirigible? - No, not aircraft.
- 飞船? - 不 不是飞行器
Sort of like more small-scale stuff, like...
小一点的东西 比如...
Well, the Glow-in-the-Dark Flashlight, that was mine.
比如夜光手电筒 那是我的发明
So this new job, do you like it?
那么你喜欢这份新工作吗?
Yeah, I like it a lot. It's exciting. It's...
是 我很喜欢 很刺激...
- What? - I'm just confused, is all.
- 怎么了? - 我只是有点奇怪
If you're not excited by it, why do you do it?
既然你一点都不兴奋 那你为什么干那个?
- I am excited by it. I just said... - I know what you said, Mr. Daley,
- 我很兴奋 我只是... - 别瞒我了 戴利先生
but what I see in front of me is a man who's lost his moxie.
我眼前这个人很明显已经丧失了激情
I have not lost my...
我没有...
I got my moxie.
我很有激情
Do you know why I became a pilot?
知道我为什么当飞行员吗?
- I don't, no. - For the fun of it.
- 不知道 - 因为那充满乐趣
Why else would anyone do anything?
没有乐趣人生还有什么意义?
Great Gatsby!
了不起的盖茨比!
Blast these pigeons and their incessant cooing!
走开 你们这些叫个不停的鸽子
- No! Mr. President! Sir! - All right. Time to see the state...
- 别! 总统先生! - 好了 是时候看看...
- Please don't get up! - of this great union! I always say,
- 请别起来! - 我们伟大的联邦了! 我总是说
leave nothing for tomorrow which can be done today.
今天能干完的事就别留到明天
Sir, if you go out there, you're gonna freak a lot of people out!
先生 你出去会吓倒一片人的
Freak? I assure you, sir, I am no freak.
吓人?胡说八道 我不是怪物
- No, I didn't mean you're a freak... - Come here, little one.
- 我不是说你是怪物... - 行了 小东西
In fact, if anyone is freakish, I'm afraid it's you, sir.
真要说吓人的话 你才吓死人了
The truth is, you are very small.
你也实在是太小了
And I mean even for a regular-sized human.
和正常人比你也算矮小的
What? Why would you even say that?
什么?为什么这么说?
I must be honest.
我是实话实说
Right. Okay, Honest Abe. Of course. I'm sorry. Great.
好吧 你很诚实 你说的对
Come, now, Mr. President, put the little man down
好了 总统先生 把小家伙放下来
and let's sit our fanny back in that throne of yours.
把你的屁股放回你的宝座上
You have a can-do attitude, and I shall do as you ask.
既然你那么坚定 那我就照办吧
Thank you.
谢谢
- There you go. - Thank you.
- 站好了 - 谢谢
It's that very can-do spirit that has defined this remarkable nation of ours.
坚定不移正是我们民族的伟大精神
- Interesting story. - They're coming.
- 我讲个故事 - 他们追来了
One night in Gettysburg...
有一天晚上在盖兹堡...
Mr. President, we're gonna need you to hold still now.
总统先生 请你先别动
- What? - Abraham, freeze!
- 什么? - 亚伯拉罕 不许动!
Freeze? I...
不许动? 我...
- Thank you. - You're welcome.
- 谢谢 - 不客气
- Come on, let's get to Air and Space. - If I may,
- 快 我们去航天航空馆 - 允许我说一句
- you two make an adorable couple. - Oh, no, we're not...
- 你们俩真是太相配了 - 不 我们不配...
No, we're not a... I mean, we're not a...
不 你搞错了...我们不是...
"We're not a... I mean, we're not a..."
什么不配不配 少来了
I never lie!
我从不撒谎
The truth is, you two are adorable together.
事实就是 你们俩个在一起太相配了
Thank you. Good night.
谢谢 晚安
Farewell, lovely lady and small, little man.
再见 美丽的女士还有小个子男人
(航天航空馆)
Now let's see if we can find these Einsteins of yours.
看看能不能找到你说的爱因斯坦们
One giant leap for a mannequin...
我的一小步 是人类的一大步
D.C., this is Air and Space. We are back online and fully operational.
华盛顿 这里是航天航空馆 全体启动 全速运行
The Tuskegee Airmen are on the march once again.
黑色轰炸机又一次开始行军
Can you stop narrating everything we're doing? Just live in the moment.
不用直播我们的每一个行动吧 享受当前的时刻吧
The Tuskegee Airmen are living in the moment!
黑色轰炸机正在享受当前的时刻
- Miss Earhart? - Yes.
- 埃尔哈特小姐 - 你好
- I wanna say thank you. - What for, Captain?
- 我想对你表示感谢 - 谢我什么 上尉?
A lot of people didn't think we could fly, either.
很多人都认为我们成不了飞行员
Thanks for clearing the runway, ma'am.
谢谢你让大家改变了想法
- Race you to Paris? - You're on!
- 比比谁先到巴黎? - 接受挑战!
No! Not now! We gotta...
不 现在不行 我们...
- It's just a quick jaunt over the pond. - No. Gotta find the Einsteins.
- 打个来回很快的 - 不行 我们是来找爱因斯坦的
Come on, we gotta go. We don't have time. Come on!
快点 我们没时间了 快
Sorry, it's in the blood.
抱歉 看到飞机我就忍不住了
There she is, Mr. Daley.
看那儿 戴利先生
Old Bessie, the old family bus. That gal took me across the Atlantic!
老贝茜 我的老搭档了 她带着我飞越了大西洋
Okay. I think the Einsteins are over here, though.
好吧 不过爱因斯坦在那边
This is Mission Control. Flight check complete.
这里是指挥中心 起飞检查完毕
- Where'd you go? Where'd they go? - You are clear for launch.
- 他们去哪儿了? - 发射准备完毕
Contact!
起飞!
D.C., this is Mission Control.
华盛顿 这里是控制中心
- No, no! No! - All systems go and green for lift-off.
- 不 不 不! - 所有系统检查完毕 准备发射
Roger that. We are green for lift-off.
收到 准备发射
No, we're definitely not green for any kind of lift-off!
不 绝对不能发射!
- I want a "go, no-go" for launch. - I say no-go. Let's not go.
- 到底发射不发射 - 我说不发射
Go!
发射!
- Go! - No! No go!
- 发射! - 不! 不能发射!
Torquing angles incoming.
启动最大扭矩
Tone it down with the torque. Torque it down.
别放大扭矩 降低扭矩
De-torque. De-torque.
降低扭矩 降低扭矩
Commence ignition sequence.
开始点火倒计时
- Roger that, flight. - We have launch commit.
- 收到 - 收到发射指令
- No. No, no, no! - Ten,
- 不 不 不 不! - 十
nine, eight, seven...
九 八 七...
- Hey, that's mine. - No, we do not have commit.
- 嘿 那是我的 - 不 没有发射指令
Repeat. We are decommissioning the committal of the launch
重复 没有发射指令
and it is now a negatory launch phase. We are in a no-fly, no-go phase.
发射指令无效 禁止发射 禁止起飞
That is a November-Gorgon phase of non-flying!
严禁任何起飞行为!
- Fine! - And we're gonna say good night.
- 好吧! - 祝各位晚安
Thank you. Good work. Over and out.
谢谢大家 干得好 完毕 解散
- Sorry. - Damn, that was disappointing.
- 对不起 - 见鬼 真扫兴
Come on. I'll buy you a cup of coffee.
来吧 我请你喝咖啡
Hey, little space monkey.
你好 太空猴
You're Able. Okay, good. How you doing?
你叫亚伯 很好 你好吗?
Yes, good. At ease. All right.
哦 很好 稍息 好的
You're a polite little fella, aren't you?
你非常有礼貌
Hey, you happen to know where those little Einstein bobblehead guys are?
你知道那些爱因斯坦摇头娃娃在哪儿吗?
Mr. Daley! I found your Einsteins.
戴利先生! 我找到爱因斯坦了
Great. Hey...
太好了...
Gentlemen, we're trying to crack the combination of this tablet doodad,
先生们 我们需要你们帮我们 破译这块金牌的密码
and the writing here says we'll find it
金牌上的文字告诉我们
if we figure out the secret at the heart of Pharaoh's tomb.
要破译密码必须破译法老墓穴深处的秘密
That's an easy one. The answer's in the question.
很简单 答案就蕴含在问题中
- What does that mean? - "Figure out".
- 什么意思? - 破译
It's a figure! I.e., a number.
就是计算 比如 一个数字
And the Pharaoh's tomb, i.e. The pyramids.
法老的墓穴 就是金字塔
Don't you get it, kid? You're looking for the secret number
还不明白吗 孩子? 你们要找的就是藏在金字塔中的
at the heart of the pyramids.
那串神秘数字
Well, whistle me Dixie, the answer's pi!
哦 我懂了 答案就是圆周率!
- Pi? - 3.14159265, to be exact.
- 圆周率? - 3.14159265 精确的来说
Yes! 3.1495265.
对! 3.1495265
No, no, no, 3.14159265.
不是 是3.14159265
Yeah, okay, 3.14...
好吧 3.14...
I'm sorry, I can't tell. Is it yes or no? Cause you just...
对不起 我实在分不清 你们是在点头还是摇头...
I know it's hard, could you just...
我知道这对你们很难 能不能...
Don't touch the hair.
别碰头发
- Sorry, I can't tell if it's up or... - I'm a bobblehead, dummkopf,
- 对不起 你们晃得我头晕... - 我是摇头娃娃 笨蛋
and that's the way we like it. All together, now!
我们就爱摇头晃脑 一起说
That's the way We like it
我们就爱摇头晃脑
You know, we can't all be Einsteins, so...
知道吗 不是人人都能当爱因斯坦...
- I can! - We are!
- 我能! - 我们是
- He is! - Me, too!
- 他是 - 我也是
- Okay, all right. - Okay, here it is.
- 好吧 - 好 我再说一遍
- Can you slow it down a little bit? - Okay.
- 可不可以说慢一点 - 好的
3.14159265.
3.14159265
- Okay. 3.14... - I've got it.
- 好的 3.14... - 我记住了
- Thank you, Mr. Einsteins. - Thank you.
- 谢谢 爱因斯坦先生 - 谢谢
All right. Now, like the brilliant and famous general that I am,
好了 作为一名伟大的将军
I thought long and hard about what you said,
经过一番深思熟虑
and I've come up with a brand-new and improved battle plan!
我又想出了全新的升级版作战计划
Okay.
听着
I will loudly announce that we are not
我会大声宣布
going to attack, and then...
全体不攻击 然后...
Wait for it.
等待时机
"What's the amazing Custer about to say now? I hope he's my friend, or..."
然后大家随便闲扯 突然
We attack!
发动攻击!
Didn't expect your friend to run off like that, did you?
没想到你的朋友自己逃命去了吧?
He's coming back, Ka-Ka-Ro.
他会回来的 妖怪
Sure as moon shines on a mongoose, he'll be here.
他很快就会回来救我
I would save my breath if I were you.
如果我是你就省点力气
You don't have many left.
你离被闷死已经不远了
We've got about 10 minutes to get over there to Jed.
还有十分钟杰德就要被淹没了
I think we make a good team, perhaps more than a team.
我觉得我们的合作很愉快 也许我们的关系能更进一步
Wait. Okay, wait.
等等 等一下
What's the matter? You didn't like kissing me?
怎么了?你不喜欢吻我吗?
No, I did. It was great. I mean, the slapping hurt a little bit, but...
不 我喜欢 感觉棒极了 被扇耳光有那么点疼 但...
- So you don't like me, then. - Of course I like you. You're incredible.
- 就是说你不喜欢我 - 我当然喜欢你 你非常特别
I think you're an amazing person. You're...
你让人无法抗拒...
It's just there are certain issues that would prevent us from...
但我们之间存在着一些障碍...
- I just... You're not... - I'm not what, Mr. Daley?
- 我只是...你不是... - 我不是什么戴利先生?
Okay. You're made of...
好吧 你的身体是...
Made of...
身体是...
Wonderful things. You're made of good, wonderful things.
美好的东西 你的身体非常美好 非常了不起
Come on.
走吧
Gentlemen, could you buy us some time please?
男士们 能帮我们挡一会儿吗?
It'll have to do.
看来只有这个办法了
No! That's the first plane ever made!
不要!那是人类发明的第一架飞机
It's made out of balsa wood and paper.
它是用木板做的纸糊的
It's made out of spruce and canvas and good old-fashioned American ingenuity.
它是用云杉木和帆布做的 汇聚了老一代美国人的精巧工艺
Are you coming, or what?
你到底上不上来?
- Out of our way! - I don't think so.
- 让开! - 没门
They're getting away!
他们逃了!
Hang on, Mr. Daley. Things are about to get interesting.
抓稳了戴利先生 这事儿越来越有意思了
A lady pilot! Preposterous!
是个女的在开!她是不是疯了
- Think again, boys! - Oh, she's good.
- 看清楚 小子们 - 哦 她飞得真好
What? What?
怎么了 怎么了?
One of the wires is jammed. I'm going to have to loosen it.
一根线卡住了 我去松开它
- Here, take the stick! - No! I'm not gonna... No!
- 你来控制方向杆 - 不 我不要!
I know you've got moxie in you yet.
我知道你还有激情
Moxie doesn't fly planes! People who have pilots' licenses fly planes!
有激情不代表会开飞机 开飞机要飞行执照的
- Okay. - She's all yours.
- 好吧 - 交给你了
I don't want it! I don't want the stick!
不要吧!我不要这个
Don't look now, Mr. Daley, but you're flying an airplane!
别到处看戴利先生 你在驾驶飞机
Able! The doors!
亚伯!开门!
- Got it! - Pull!
- 行了! - 下降!
Pull up!
拉升!
Yes!
好样的!
Godspeed, Amelia Earhart!
一路顺风 阿梅莉亚·埃尔哈特
Godspeed.
一路顺风
Look a little nervous there, Ramen Noodle.
你有点紧张啊 蠢猪
'Cause for me, this is like a spa treatment.
我就当是做热沙按摩
Sand baths are really rejuvenating for the skin. Exfoliates.
沙浴能帮助我恢复活力 去角质的
Giving up yet?
你放弃了吧
Not quite yet, no.
还没有
In fact, let's see if we can't make time fly.
我可以让时间流逝的更快些
What is that funny sound?
什么怪声音?
Stop!
站住!
Right there, please, Mr. Daley.
站住别动 戴利先生
Well. Well, well, well!
哇 哇...
You certainly know how to make an entrance, Mr. Daley.
你的出场很漂亮啊 戴利先生
Time to recruit some backup.
该去挖点援军来了
I hope for your little friend's sake, here,
你朋友快淹死了
that you also figured out the combination.
但愿你已经想到了密码
- Give me Jed. - Oh, no, no, no.
- 把杰德给我 - 哦 不不不
First, give me the combination and hand over that tablet.
先给我密码 还有金牌
I'll give you the tablet and the combination
我会把金牌和密码给你
when you release my friends and give him back to me.
不过你先放了我的朋友们 还有把他给我
I shall release what I want to release the moment I want to release it.
我愿意什么时候放人就什么时候放人
Great. And I'll release what I want to release
好极了 那我什么时候愿意给你
at the exact moment that I want to release it, okay?
我就什么时候给你 怎么样?
Tell me the combination and give me that tablet right now
给我密码和金牌 马上
or I shall kill all of your friends,
否则我就杀光你的朋友
starting with the little shaggy-headed little cowman here.
首先拿这个胡子拉楂的小牛仔开刀
I ain't shaggy-headed! Gigantor, let me take this guy!
我才不胡子拉楂 铁人 把这个坏蛋交给我
Don't worry, I got this handled. You don't want to give me my friends,
别担心 我能处理 你不先放了我的朋友
then you're not gonna get your combination or your tablet.
你就别想拿到密码和金牌
- All right, I'll tell you what. - Good.
- 好吧 你给我听好 - 好的
They didn't call me Kahmunrah the Trustworthy for nothing.
我的外号不是什么值得信赖的卡门拉
Here you go. They didn't call me Kahmunrah the Trustworthy!
给你 我的外号不叫值得信赖的卡门拉
They called me Kahmunrah the Bloodthirsty,
他们叫我嗜血卡门拉
who kills whoever doesn't give Kahmunrah exactly what he wants
这个卡门拉想要什么
in the moment that he wants it, which is right now,
就要立刻得到
when I had also better get the combination and the tablet!
这个卡门拉现在要的就是金牌和密码
- That's what they called you? - It was shorter in Egyptian.
- 你的外号很长啊 - 用埃及语会短一些
Great, I'll give you the combination after you give him back.
很好 把他给我 我就给你密码和金牌
How dare you? If you touch that again, I shall kill you right now.
我看你再敢碰它一下 我就立刻杀了你
- Okay. - Do not touch this.
- 好吧 - 别碰它
- This is a no-touching zone! - Good. Well, then...
- 这里是禁止触碰区域! - 好 好吧...
Oh, my God! I can't believe you reached across like that again!
哦上帝 我简直不敢相信你又过界了
I can't even believe it! Oh, God, I want to kill you right...
难以置信 上帝 我真想马上杀了你...
If you didn't know this combination, you'd be so dead right now,
要不是你知道密码 你早就没命了
- it would be unbelievable. - Great, but I do know the combination.
- 你会死的很难看 - 可惜我知道密码
Don't cross this line with your hand!
不许你的手越过这条线
How dare you! If you speak again, I'm going to kill you.
胆大包天!如果你再啰嗦一句 我就杀了你
Do you understand this?
听明白没有?
Don't say it! Oh, God, I see you getting ready.
不许说话 上帝 我看到你嘴巴动了
- I wasn't gonna say anything. - Oh, my God, don't say anything.
- 我没想开口说话 - 哦 上帝 不许说话
I shall murder you if you talk again.
你再说一句我就掐死你
Now give me that tablet and tell me the combination.
把金牌和密码给我
Okay. After you give me Jed and release my friends.
可以 你先放了杰德还有我的朋友
- You did all three! - What?
- 你又犯规了 - 什么?
You spoke and you reached your hand across!
你不仅说话了而且又把手伸过来了
Look. I can talk to you about this all night, okay?
听着 我可以跟你绕一晚上
- How about this? - Look, just give...
- 不如这样 - 你给我听好...
How about I don't kill you right now, like I really, really want to,
我可以先不杀你 虽然我很想很想杀了你
and I give you precisely five seconds
我给你五秒钟的时间
to give me that tablet and tell me the combination?
交出金牌和密码
We already got the combination. It's pi.
我们知道密码了 是圆周率
- 3.14159265. - No!
- 3.14159265 - 不!
- Hey. - Sorry.
- 嘿 - 对不起
So Crazy Hair here, he sang. Oh, did he sing! Like a canary.
这个怪老头 还会唱歌 唱起来像只金丝雀
I'm sorry, Larry.
对不起 拉瑞
Enough out of you! Remember what happened last time?
你少废话!忘了教训了?
- That's enough. - Stupid man.
- 住手 - 蠢货
- You okay? - Yeah, thanks.
- 你没事吧? - 没事 谢谢
Must be a real bummer for you, Larry,
你肯定气坏了吧 拉瑞
knowing that all of your valiant efforts were, in the end, for naught.
你失去了所有的筹码
What a terrible disappointment you must be to yourself.
你肯定沮丧到不行
Do you hear that humming sound?
听到嗡嗡声了没有?
Do you know what that sound is?
知道这是什么声音吗?
It's rhetorical.
我在用修辞
That is the sound of the End.
那就是末日的声音
I'm sorry, Jed.
对不起 杰德
You did your best, Gigantor.
你尽力了铁人
Dadgum it, we almost had him, too.
见鬼 我们差点就赢了
No, I mean, I'm sorry I wasn't around the last couple of years at the museum.
不 我是说我很抱歉 前几年我一直不在博物馆
- Maybe none of this would have happened. - You don't get it, do you, Gigantor?
- 否则这一切都不会发生 - 你还不明白吗 铁人?
I didn't call you 'cause we needed your help.
我打给你不是我们需要帮助
Sure, we were in a little pickle,
我们确实有点小麻烦
but it wouldn't have been the first time
但这不是我第一次
I had to wrestle my way out of a root sack.
被沙紧紧地埋在下面
No, partner. I called you 'cause you needed us.
不是 伙计 我打给你是因为你需要我们
That fancy suit you've been parading around in these past couple years,
这几年来你一直把自己隐藏在 那套光鲜的西服里
that there's a hanging suit.
但在我看来 那只是一个躯壳
All gussied up, but dead inside.
如同行尸走肉
That ain't you.
那不是你
- And I'll tell you another thing. - Yeah.
- 还有件事 - 什么
This night ain't over yet.
今夜还没结束
This little Midnight Cowboy's got some fight left in him.
我这个小小的午夜牛仔 还有无穷的战斗力
Something tells me you do, too. Ho, now!
你也有 不要气馁
Welcome to the new, extended reign of Kahmunrah,
卡门拉的统治时代到来了
Fifth King of Egypt
埃及第五代君王
and now the world!
现在将统治世界!
Horus, Ra, my warriors, come forth!
我的军队 前进!
Send Larry Daley and his friends to their doom!
把拉瑞·戴利和他的朋友送进地狱!
Halt!
住手!
The mighty Octavius has returned!
伟大的奥克塔维厄斯回来了!
I ride on the back of nature's most fearsome creature! I ride
我骑着全世界最最令人闻风丧胆的动物 我骑着
the squirrel!
一只松鼠!
Forward now, my mighty steed!
前进 我的战马!
Whoa, girl! Easy.
悠着点 姑娘
Do you wish to surrender honorably?
你选择缴械投降
Or must this end with the spilling of your blood?
还是血溅沙场?
This? This is your big rescue?
就这个?这就是你的援军?
Oh, no. This is!
不 这才是!
What is that thing?
这是什么东西?
The name is Abraham Lincoln.
我是亚伯拉罕·林肯
- And you, sir, are in a heap of trouble! - Attack it!
- 先生 你的麻烦大了 - 杀了他!
Disgusting half-pigeons!
恶心的半鸟人
No, no, no! Hello?
不 不 不!等等!
Adios, bird brains!
滚吧 鸟人
Wait, wait, wait. No, no!
等等 等等 别!
Goodbye, strange birdmen.
再见了 鸟人
Do not return to the Underworld!
别回地下世界!
Yes, yes, do go back into the Underworld!
对 对 回你们老家去吧!
Thank you for coming! Good night!
谢谢光临 晚安!
No, no!
不 不!
Oh, this is awkward.
真是尴尬
It appears my work here is done.
这儿好象没我什么事了
Just remember, son, a house divided against itself cannot stand.
记住我的话孩子 家庭不睦 万事不兴
Farewell.
再见
- What now? - You know, I'm not quite sure.
- 现在怎么办? - 我也不知道怎么办
I suppose we should probably start by watching him die.
我要看到他死
Streltsy! Make him dead!
士兵 杀了他
Now what?
又怎么了?
We are not going to attack right
我们现在不准备
now!
攻击!
Get them!
给我上!
Fear not, Larry! I will help Jedediah!
别担心 拉瑞 我去救杰迪戴亚!
You come at them from behind!
你去后面包抄
- Hey, what's going on? - I'm hiding.
- 嘿 你在干嘛? - 我在找地方隐蔽
Hiding? What are you doing? Come on, we need you.
隐蔽?你在搞什么! 快 我们这儿需要你
- I'm a failure. - No, you're not.
- 我是个失败者 - 不 你不是
Did you foolishly lead 208 Americans to their deaths
小比格霍恩河战役 我领导208个美国人打仗 最后全军覆灭
at the Battle of Little Bighorn?
你尝过这种滋味吗?
- No. - No? Not good. Not good at all.
- 没有 - 没有 那感觉不好 真的不好
- That's not good. - Sure, I talk a good game,
- 感觉不好 - 当然 我也就能动动嘴皮子
but the truth of the matter is, I don't deserve these stars.
干真的不行 我不配肩膀上的军衔
I will always be famous for my biggest failure.
人们永远只记得我的失败
Hey.
嘿
The past is the past, okay?
过去的就让它过去 好吗?
Right now, this moment, this night,
现在 当下 就在今夜
this is what you're gonna be remembered for.
这场战役将永垂青史
This is your last stand.
这是你的最后一战
- They need a leader. - Yeah, they need a leader.
- 我们需要一位领袖 - 是啊 他们需要领袖
Yeah? You want to be their leader, huh?
是吗?你愿意去领导他们吗?
- Yeah, I do. - Let's do this!
- 是 我愿意 - 那就站起来!
- All right? - Yeah.
- 怎么样? - 好
Let's go!
我们走!
Not good!
太糟了!
Larry!
拉瑞!
Hey, Able!
嘿 亚伯!
I want to help!
我需要帮助
Oh, great.
哦 好的
Who are you? This is my museum!
你是谁?这是我的博物馆
Well, he's my human. Back off!
他是我的人 你走开
You need all the help you can get, Jungle-Dweller!
你尽管拉人 你这个野蛮人
Get over yourself space snob!
少废话 你这个太空佬
Guys! Hey, guys!
伙计们!嘿 伙计们!
This is not the time to get into this, all right?
现在不是争这些的时候 好吗?
Dexter, you know better.
德克斯特 你知道规矩
All right? That's what happens when you do that!
好吗 再胡闹就请你们吃耳光
You get that.
给你一耳光
Stop! Just stop! Stop!
住手 都给我住手!
Now, listen. You're both proud capuchin!
听着 你们都是高贵的僧帽猴
You need to concentrate on slapping the enemy!
应该一直对外 抗击外敌
Keep it together, all right?
团结起来 行吗?
Come on, let's go! Let's do it!
快 冲上去 给我打
- Jedediah! They need us! - I ain't gonna make it!
- 杰迪戴亚 大家需要我们 - 我恐怕不行了
Afraid this cowboy's been to his last hoedown.
恐怕我的日子到头了
Octavius, remember me as I was, wild, and free, and...
奥克塔维厄斯 记住我的精神 自由 狂野...
- No need for final words. - I'm not finished yet.
- 还不是说遗言的时候 - 我还没说完
I want to get to the story of our relationship,
我还想回忆一下我们的那段事
the evolution from enemy to friends.
我们是怎么从敌人变成朋友的
- No! - It'll make you cry!
- 不要! - 你想哭就哭吧!
No! Because you are going to live!
不!因为你还死不了!
- Let's go to work. - Have a sword.
- 该我们上场了 - 拿着剑
Sword!
拿剑来!
Incoming!
上面!
That smarts.
好疼
You smack, you kick! You smack, you kick!
你打 你踢! 你打 你踢!
You smack, you kick! Teamwork, fellas! Wunderbar!
你打 你踢! 干得漂亮 伙计们!
How you doing, fellas?
你们好啊 伙计们!
- Are you all right? - Never better.
- 你还好吗? - 再好没有
Listen, when I give you the signal, I want you to open the gate.
听着 一看到我的信号就立刻打开门
- I take it you have a plan. - I'm gonna divide the house.
- 看来你成竹在胸 - 我要去搞点小破坏
The tablet! Now!
金牌给我 马上!
Okay, sure, you can have it.
好的 当然 我会给你
Just tell me who the boss is and I'll give it to you.
告诉我你们谁是头 我就给他
Or should I give it to Kahmunrah? He's your master, right?
要不我给卡门拉? 他看上去是你们头 不是吗?
- Nyet! He is not our master! - Really? 'Cause he acts like he is.
- 放屁 他才不是什么头 - 是吗? 我看一直是他在说了算
But fine, just tell me who the boss is and you can have it.
算了 你就告诉我你们谁是头 我就给谁
Hey! That'd be me.
我是头!
This man is a peasant! I am the only one here of noble birth!
他是个农民 我才是这里唯一有贵族血统的人
Really? 'Cause he's got more medals and a bigger hat, but...
是吗?可是他看上去有更多勋章 帽子也更大 不过...
- Thank you. - You might got a lot of medals,
- 谢谢 - 你确实有很多勋章
but you put one of your little child hands on that tablet again,
但是你要再敢用你的小手碰一下金牌
it'll be the last thing them tiny little mitts of yours ever touch.
我就要你好看
Why would you touch little Nippy?
你干嘛要伤害小拿拿?
I can handle this, okay?
我能自己解决 好吗?
You can handle nothing! You can barely speak, you fool!
你什么也解决不了 你连话都说不清楚 蠢货!
You know what? No problem. I'll give it to you. You see that?
没问题 你要是吗 我给你
Oh, you're a spunky little fella!
你这个小杂种
Very clever, Mr. Daley, getting them to fight amongst themselves.
干得漂亮 戴利先生 让他们自相残杀
Yeah. I can't really take credit. It was Abraham Lincoln's idea.
对 我不敢邀功 这主意是亚伯拉罕·林肯想出来的
You know, a house divided can't...
家庭不睦 万事不兴...
- Doesn't do well. - Yes, well,
- 还做得不够 - 没错
you should have saved yourself when you had the chance,
刚才你就应该自己逃命的
because now I shall have the tremendous pleasure
可惜你又落在了我手里
of killing you myself!
我现在最想做的事就是亲手杀了你
What are you?
你到底是什么人?
I'm the night guard.
我是个守卫
No!
不!
Victory is ours!
胜利属于我们!
Yeah!
是
That's what I'm talking about!
我说什么来着!
Yeah!
是的
I'd say somebody found his moxie.
我看到有个人终于找回他的激情了
The Battle of the Smithsonian.
史密森尼战役
Perhaps the greatest battle the world will never know.
将是一场永远不为人知的伟大战役
We'll know.
我们都见证了
Yeah.
是啊
Oh, man, I got an hour till sunrise. I got to get you guys back.
噢 老天 还有一个小时就天亮了 我得把你们都弄回去
In case you forgot, Gigantor, they don't want us there anymore.
我不得不提醒你铁人 那儿的人不再需要我们了
Well, I do.
不 我需要
Hey, think you could hook us up with a ride?
嘿 可以载我们一程吗?
My pleasure, of course.
当然 我很荣幸
Hang on a second. One last thing I got to take care of.
稍等 我还有件事要办
Come on, boy! Come on, come on!
快 孩子!来啊
Get in there!
跳进去!
Feels good, right?
很舒服吧?
You're welcome! Just get back inside by sunrise, okay?
别客气! 记得天亮前一定要回去!
These are promising days, indeed.
这真是一个光明的时代
All right. Hey, come on, guys.
好了 伙计们 动作快
Remember, stay with your buddy, all right?
记得和同伴呆在一起
Good, good.
好 好
Well, you're back where you belong.
好了 你回到该回的地方了
Yeah. Think so.
我想是的
I guess I should be going.
我想我该走了
Hey, Amelia.
阿梅莉亚
That thing that I was trying to tell you about earlier...
早些时候我想告诉你的那件事...
There's not really an easy way to put this,
我真的很难说出口
- but, in the morning... - I know what's coming, Mr. Daley.
- 但是 一旦天亮... - 我知道会发生什么 戴利先生
I've always known.
我一直知道
But it doesn't matter.
不过没关系
You've given me the adventure of a lifetime in one night.
在一夜之间 你给了我一生都未曾体验过的冒险经历
And I have a feeling it's going to be a beautiful sunrise.
我觉得今天的日出一定特别美丽
Have fun.
要快乐
Thanks.
谢谢
I don't know about you fellas, but this old cowboy just got to second base.
不知道你怎么想 伙计 可这个老牛仔才攻到二垒
- There she goes. - Straight towards...
- 她飞走了 - 头也不回...
Canada.
加拿大
She's heading to Canada.
她在往加拿大飞
No, now she course-corrected.
航向正确
Here, head on downstairs, guys.
去地下室 伙计们
- All righty. - Good night, Larry.
- 好的 - 晚上好 拉瑞
Hey, boy, how's it going?
孩子 你好吗?
Lawrence! Bless you for bringing them back.
劳伦斯!谢谢你把他们都带回来
And might I say, a hearty well-done is in order.
你干的真是太漂亮了
And may I also point out, they cannot hide in the basement forever.
可是他们不能在地下室躲一辈子
Yeah. No, I think I got that figured out.
不 我已经想到办法了
- Really? - Yeah.
- 真的 - 对
Sun come, dum-dum.
日出 笨瓜
Our moai friend is right. The dawn will soon be upon us.
我们摩艾朋友说的对 日出即将来临
Hey, Teddy.
泰德
Remember the other night you were saying something
还记得那天晚上你和我说的吗
about the key to happiness?
你说幸福的关键是
- Did I? - You said, The key to happiness is...
- 我说了吗? - 你说 幸福的关键是...
And then the sun came up and you froze.
然后太阳出来你就冻住了
- I think I got it figured out. - Yes?
- 我想我知道答案了 - 是吗?
It's doing what you love, isn't it? With people you love.
就是做你爱做的事 对不对 和你爱的人在一起
Actually, I was going to say "physical exercise",
其实 我想说的是"锻炼身体"
but the love thing's good, too.
不过你说的也不错
- Lawrence! - Yeah.
- 劳伦斯 - 什么
Welcome home, son.
欢迎回家 孩子
Thanks.
谢谢
Well, folks, the wait is over. After two months of renovation,
朋友们 漫长的等待终于结束 经过了2个月的整修
tonight, The Museum of Natural History reopens its doors to the public.
今夜 自然历史博物馆将重新对公众开放
As you can see, New Yorkers are flooding in,
如你所见 纽约市民正迫不及待的涌进博物馆
eager to see just what changes are in store.
想亲身体验博物馆
With its new, extended night hours,
新推出的夜游项目
we're told the museum will be more lively than ever.
据说夜间博物馆的展品 比以往更加栩栩如生
- Well, well, well, well! - Hey.
- 好啊 好啊 好啊 - 嘿
I see the uniform still fits after these long, long years.
都过了这么久了 这身制服倒还合身
Yeah, yeah. Really hasn't been that long, but...
是啊 不过也没过多久嘛...
So, to what do we owe this "triumphant" return?
那么 这场喜庆回归的代价是什么?
Not cut out for the "corporate" jungle after all. Got fired.
还是适应不了商场 被裁了?
No, actually, I sold my company.
实际上 我把公司卖了
The world doth move in mysterious ways.
这个世界的变化令人难以捉摸
One day, we've got to get rid of everything old,
前一天我们还在清理所有老展品
the next, a rich, anonymous donor gives a huge endowment.
后一天 一个富有的无名氏 突然捐助了博物馆一大笔资金
With a proviso: Everything stays the same. So...
条件就是 保持所有老展品不变...
- Well, not exactly the same, obviously. - No.
- 很明显 也不是一点没变 - 不是
Bully, lads and ladies, the name is Theodore Roosevelt,
注意 女士们先生们 我是西奥多·罗斯福
naturalist, Rough Rider and twenty-sixth President of these great United States.
一个自然主义者 又名狂野骑士 美国的第26任总统
Come along, lad. The hunt is afoot. Lawrence.
跟上 孩子 冒险开始 劳伦斯
Hey, you dum-dums bring me gum-gum?
嘿 你们这些笨瓜给我带口香糖吗?
My parents gave me this tablet some 3,000 years ago,
大约3000年前 我父母给了我这块金牌
entrusting me with one of my people's most prized possessions.
这是埃及人民最至高无上的宝物
- Does it do anything? - Do anything?
- 它有什么用? - 什么用?
Yeah. What's the point if it doesn't do anything?
对 如果没用的话要它来干嘛?
Tell 'em
告诉他们
Actually, it has a magical power that brings all the exhibits to life.
实际上 它是一块复活金牌 可以让这里的展览品都活过来
No, really, what's it do?
好了 别开玩笑 它到底有什么用?
Nothing. It's just for decoration.
没用 只是装饰品
I knew it.
我就知道
This place is lame. This thing doesn't even look real.
这里烂透了 这个恐龙看上去一点都不真实
Seriously, dude, these animatronics suck.
没错 老兄 这里的电动技术太落后了
- Mammoth? - Yeah.
- 猛犸象? - 是啊
Extinct!
绝种了!
- Today's technology is beyond me. - I know. It's so lifelike.
- 我已经跟不上科技发展了 - 是啊 做的像真的一样
- Yeah, yeah, yeah. - Something else.
- 是的 是的 - 问你件事
You'll stick around a bit longer this time,
这次你打算做久一点
or you gonna run away again when you get something better?
还是像上次一样干了一半 又去干别的?
- I'm gonna stay. - Stay, for a long time.
- 我会呆下去 - 一直呆下去?
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- 是的 - 是的
Good. 'Cause, as night guards go, you're...
很好 作为一个守卫 你...
- What? - The best.
- 什么? - 是最棒的
Excuse me.
我没听清
You, the toddler! Don't hug the displays.
你 小孩!不可以抱展览品
I'm sorry. Hi.
打扰了 你好
I don't mean to stare. I just...
请原谅我的冒昧 我只是...
You look a lot like somebody I know, and...
你和我认识的一个人长得很像...
I get that a lot.
很多人都这么说
- Do you? - Yeah. I guess I have that kind of face.
- 是吗? - 对 可能是我长了一张大众脸吧
- Familiar. - Yeah.
- 大众脸 - 是啊
You're not by any chance related to Amelia Earhart, are you?
你不会碰巧和阿梅莉亚·埃尔哈特 有什么亲属关系吧
- No. - No.
- 没有 - 没有
- No, I don't think so. - Of course you're not.
- 我想没有 - 当然没有
- I mean, I don't know. Maybe I'm... - I just had to ask. I'm sorry.
- 我不知道 也许... - 我只是忍不住想问 抱歉
She was that woman who flew across the Pacific.
她是那个第一个飞越太平洋的女性吧
- The Atlantic. - Atlantic. Of course.
- 大西洋 - 对 是大西洋
First woman to fly across the Atlantic, and she received the Flying Cross,
第一个飞越大西洋的女性 她还获得过飞行十字勋章
first woman to do that.
女性当中也是第一个
- That's very cool. - Yeah, she was cool.
- 真酷啊 - 对 她真的很酷
Hey, you know what you should check out is the the Hall of Miniatures.
你应该去微缩模型馆看看
Could you take me there? I'm always getting lost.
你能给我带路吗?我总是迷路
Yeah, I know. Sure. Yeah, I'll show you. Come on.
好的 当然 我来带路 来吧
Thank you.
谢谢
- I'm Larry Daley. - Tess.
- 我叫拉瑞·戴利 - 苔丝
- Joseph, time for dinner! - One second, Ma!
- 约瑟夫 吃晚饭了! - 马上来 妈妈
Joey Motorola, you get down here for supper right now!
乔伊·摩托罗拉 马上给我下楼吃饭!
I said one second, Ma! I really think I'm on to something here!
我说了马上来 妈 我正在研究一个很重要的东西